<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A caveat to the standing Christian, and to him that thinketh he standeth by William Gearing ...</title>
            <author>Gearing, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1666</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 125 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42544</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G433</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14121</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12335964</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12335964</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59782</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42544)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59782)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 211:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A caveat to the standing Christian, and to him that thinketh he standeth by William Gearing ...</title>
                  <author>Gearing, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>61 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Crook ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1666.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59782:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59782:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CAVEAT TO THE Standing Chriſtian, AND To him that thinketh he ſtandeth.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>WILLIAM GEARING</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>Quòd renati poſſunt ruere in peccatum grave, ſatis oſtendunt triſtiſſimi lapſus ſanctiſſimorum hominum. <bibl>
                  <hi>Urſin. Catech. de diſcrimin. peccat.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Crook,</hi> at the Ship in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1666.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:59782:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59782:2"/>
            <p>Unto the Right Worſhipful Sir <hi>THOMAS STEVENS</hi> OF Little <hi>SADB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RY</hi> IN THE COUNTY of <hi>GLOCESTER,</hi> KNIGHT; And to the Virtuous LADY HIS WIFE, <hi>WILLIAM GEARING</hi> Dedicateth this enſuing Diſcourſe, Enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>A Caveat to the ſtanding Chriſtian,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:59782:3"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:59782:3"/>
            <head>A Caveat to the ſtanding Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and to him that thinketh he ſtandeth.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Corinth. 10.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Wherefore let him that thinketh he ſtandeth, take heed leſt he fall.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The Introduction.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Do not know a more ſeaſonable Exhortation then this of the Apoſtle; it is indeed <hi>verbum diei in die ſuo,</hi> we living in ſuch times wherein men fall into irreligiouſneſs and all manner of profaneneſs. Our Saviour ſpeaking of the Signs before his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, foretells how the Stars ſhall fall from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>Math.</hi> 24.29. Some underſtand by Stars eminent Profeſſors, and by Heaven the Church: If this be true, then that Scri ture is this day fulfilled; many Stars are already fallen, and others fall daily: So that if ever a word of Exhortation to quicken Profeſſors to heedfulneſs and circumſpection be ſeaſonable, now it is; every Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59782:4"/> ſhould now lift up his voice like a Trumpet, and cry aloud,
<q>Let him that thinketh he ſtandeth, take heed leſt he fall.</q>
               </p>
               <p>For Coherence.] The Apoſtle in the preceding verſes ſets before the <hi>Corinthians</hi> eyes a Map of <hi>Iſraels</hi> provocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and of <hi>Iſraels</hi> puniſhments, of Gods exemplary judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on them: Vengeance follows ſin as the thread fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows the needle; if ſin be in the houſe, judgment is at the door.</p>
               <p>Their capital ſins were,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Their luſting after evil things; which Interpreters underſtand of their luſting after fleſh,<note place="margin">Ver. 6 of this Chap.</note> 
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 11.4. The token of Gods diſpleaſure againſt them, was his giving them Quails in wrath, and a ſore Plague to boot, <hi>Numb.</hi> 11.33.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A ſecond ſin mentioned was Idolatry, mentioned in the ſeventh verſe of this Chapter; of which we read <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.4.8. <hi>They made them a molten Calf, and worſhipped it, and ſacrificed thereunto, ſaying, Theſe be thy Gods O Iſrael, which have brought thee up out of the Land of Egypt.</hi> Gods judgment upon them for this ſin, was the Sword, by which there fell three thouſand, <hi>ver.</hi> 28.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third ſin mentioned was fornication, <hi>ver.</hi> 8. a venial ſin in the account of the profane; and yet this ſin was dyed in the blood of three and twenty thouſand, <hi>Num.</hi> 25.9.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A fourth ſin was tempting of Chriſt, <hi>ver.</hi> 9. menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned <hi>Num.</hi> 21.6. For this ſin God was avenged on them by ſtinging them with fiery Serpents.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The laſt ſin was murmuring, the ſin of <hi>Corah</hi> and his confederates, who murmured againſt <hi>Moſes:</hi> The mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murers were deſtroyed of the Deſtroyer; God ſent an Angel, called here a Deſtroyer, whether a good Angel or evil 'tis not determined, and he deſtroyed them. Thus you ſee how God paid thoſe ſinners their deſerved wages; every ſin like the Cockatrice hath a ſting of wrath in the tail.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:59782:4"/>
               <p>In the eleventh verſe he gives a Reaſon why their ſins and Gods judgments ſtand upon Record in Scripture: Now all theſe things <hi>(i.)</hi> all theſe dreadful judgments were inflicted on them <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as types or examples in reſpect of us. <hi>They are written for our admonition, upon whom the ends of the world are come:</hi> They are ſtanding monuments of Gods wrath to all ages, even to the end of the world, that none in all ages may run into the ſame ſins, and ſo partake of the ſame Plagues: God is as juſt to day as yeſterday, and hates ſin to day as yeſterday: If we commit fornication, if we tempt Chriſt, if we mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and God; if we ſin as they did, he will viſit us with the Sword, with the Plague, with Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, with a Deſtroyer, as he did them: Where like ſins abound, expect the like judgments.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>NOw from theſe examples of Gods wrath, and Gods end in ſetting up theſe monuments of his indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he takes occaſion to exhort us againſt carnal ſecurity and confidence, and ſo much the rather becauſe we live in the ends of the world, in the corrupteſt ages and times.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherefore let him that thinketh he ſtandeth,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>In the words we have four parts.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A Diſeaſe; the Falling-ſickneſs.] <hi>Leſt ye fall: (i.)</hi> fall into ſin, fall into the hands of the living God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A Remedy preſcribed; Circumſpection or heedful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our ſelves.] <hi>Take heed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The perſon moſt ſubject to this Diſeaſe, and for whom the Remedy is good.] <hi>Him that thinketh he ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. The Reaſon why we ſhould take heed, expreſs'd in that word <hi>Wherefore.] (i.)</hi> Seeing others fell into grievous ſins, and God viſited them with dreadful Plagues, do you therefore take heed.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:59782:5"/>
               <p>For explication of the words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let him that thinketh]</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Qui videtur:</hi> which in our Tranſlation is ſometimes rendred, <hi>he thinketh,</hi> and ſometimes, <hi>he ſeemeth:</hi> Some there are that think it to be a meer expletive particle, which rather filleth up the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence then addeth any thing to the ſenſe: Mr. <hi>Iſaac Cauſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſaac Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſab. in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitol. pag. 180.</note> citeth divers places in the <hi>Roman</hi> Hiſtorians, in which this word is ſo uſed; among the reſt there is one out of <hi>Capitolinus,</hi> where ſpeaking of a certain Poem, he ſaith, <hi>Epigramma videtur extare,</hi> the Epigram ſeemeth to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant; and then preſently ſets down the Epigram it ſelf, where to ſeem to be extant, and to be extant is all one. <hi>Salmaſius</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Salmaſ. in Jul. Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolin. pag. 106.</note> hath gathered divers ſayings to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, both in Hiſtorians and other Writers. Others have obſerved the like manner of ſpeech even out of the Holy Scriptures, ſuch as theſe are; <hi>If any man ſeem to be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16. that is, if any man be contentious. And <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.1.<note place="margin">Hoord, Souls mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery and recov. c. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Let us fear, leſt a promiſe being left us of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into his reſt, any of you ſhould ſeem to come ſhort of it;</hi> that is, leſt any of you ſhould come ſhort. In like ſort, <hi>Mark</hi> 10.42 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>They that ſeem to bear rule over the Gentiles,</hi> as our old Tranſlation rendred it, is no more but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>They that do bear rule over the Gentiles:</hi> So ſay they here, <hi>He thinketh,</hi> or <hi>he ſeemeth,</hi> is a meer expletive particle without any ſignification. But I ſuppoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is thus to be rendred,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> pro existimare, videri ſibi eſt, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lſo praeſumere. <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>vanel.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Qui ſibi videtur,</hi> he that ſeemeth to himſelf to ſtand, he that hath this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of himſelf that he ſtandeth, he that pleaſeth hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſelf with his own conceit of the firmneſs of his eſtate, he that thinketh</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He ſtandeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Qui ſibi placet in opinione conſtantiae quaſi liceat ſecure vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere. <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat. Schol. in loc.</hi>
                  </note>That is, 1. He that thinketh he is in the faith. 2. That he is in the ſtate of grace. 3. That he ſhall continue and perſevere to the end in the ſtate of grace: Let him</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take heed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] Let him ſee to himſelf, let him have a watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful eye over himſelf,</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:59782:5"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leſt he fall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Leſt he fall into ſin: So falling is taken ſometimes, <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.2. In many things <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, we ſtumble, and fall: This fall woundeth and bruiſeth the Conſcience.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Leſt he fall from the faith into errour, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3. The Apoſtle ſpeaks of a falling away before the coming of Chriſt: to fall there, is to depart from the faith and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Chriſt unto hereſie and idolatry.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Leſt he fall away from the truths and ways of God. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.10. <hi>If they fall away.</hi>] Of all falls the moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous; for ſuch ſtumble and fall, and never riſe more; they never ceaſe falling till they fall headlong into Hell: Such was the fall of Angels from Heaven into Hell.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Leſt he fall: <hi>(i.)</hi> leſt he periſh for ever; let him take heed leſt he fall into everlaſting deſtruction. Old <hi>Simeon</hi> ſaid of the holy Child Jeſus to <hi>Mary</hi> his Mother, <hi>Behold this Child is ſet for the fall—of many, Luke</hi> 2.34. <hi>(i.)</hi> he is appointed for the ruine and deſtruction of many, who ſhall ſtumble at Chriſt, and fall into the Sea of deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. All theſe falls are comprehended in this word in my Text.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Some Objections for the cleering this Text anſwered.</head>
               <p>BEfore I come to raiſe any Obſervations from theſe words, I muſt cleer two things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 1. The Papiſts argue from this place, that none can be certain of their Salvation; for (ſay they) if thoſe that ſtand muſt fear leſt they fall, then we cannot be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, but be always doubting.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. The Apoſtle doth not ſay, <hi>He that ſtandeth</hi>] but <hi>he that thinketh he ſtandeth;</hi> he that conceiveth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be in the ſtate of grace; he who preſumes to ſtand: This Exhortation is principally directed to the Chriſtians that are carnally ſecure.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:59782:6"/>2. This Exhortation to holy circumſpection and heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs doth not deſtroy Aſſurance, but is an help to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve Aſſurance: He that takes moſt heed to himſelf, walks moſt ſurely: Holy circumſpection is a pillar to uphold Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance: Preſumptuous children do catch moſt falls, when as the wary do eſcape.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Certainty of Salvation and a filial fear may well ſtand together; it caſteth out ſlaviſh fear, but it ſtands with filial fear: <hi>Bleſſed is the man that feareth always, Prov.</hi> 28.14. that feareth to diſpleaſe God. Filial fear is joyned with the certainty of Salvation, ſervile fear with the fear of Damnation,<note place="margin">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Sutton in Rom. 11.20. Magdeb. Cent. 13. cap. 4.</note> ſaith a Judicious Divine of ours. The more curious difference of theſe two may he had from <hi>Aquinas</hi> and <hi>Bonaventure,</hi> noted by the <hi>Magdeburgenſes:</hi> A holy and reverential awe of God in the heart, makes a man to take heed to his ways, that he may pleaſe God: What better means can there be to keep Aſſurance?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 2. Here it may be demanded, whether this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation may not belong to the godly, who do ſtand re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſeemingly?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> Yes: for though they cannot fall totally and final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the ſtate of grace, yet godly men may fall,</p>
               <p n="1">1. From gracious acts, though not from gracious ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits.</p>
               <p n="2">2. From degrees of grace; they may fall from their firſt-love, though not from love it ſelf; <hi>à tanto,</hi> not <hi>à toto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. They may fall from their comforts, and for a time may loſe the joy of Gods ſalvation: <hi>David</hi> by his ſin, had deprived himſelf of that joyful ſenſe of Gods love which he had before; therefore he prayeth, <hi>Reſtore to me the joy of thy ſalvation, Pſal</hi> 51.12. In thoſe that are truly god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">In verè piis ineſt vera pax conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae, vera mundities cordis, vera fiducia in Deum, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra acceden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di ad De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um parrheſis, verum gandium, vera falutis certitude: H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s spirit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Sancti mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; frullu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ex animis pierum cum peccant, etſi non penitàs, magna tamen ex parte excuti, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> neget? <hi>Zanch. miſcel. lib. 1.</hi> Fideles in atrocia peccata lapſi, ſenſum gratia Dei ad tempus amittunt. <hi>Theol. Palat.</hi>
                  </note> ſaith <hi>Zanchy,</hi> there is a true peace of conſcience, true purity of heart, a lively confidence in God, true boldneſs of acceſs to God, true joy, true aſſurance of ſalvation: But that theſe motions and fruits of the Spirit are greatly, though not wholly, ſhaken out of the ſouls of the godly when they ſin, who is there that will deny? And ſay the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59782:6"/> 
                  <hi>Palatine</hi> Divines, The faithful when they fall into groſs ſins, do loſe the feeling of Gods favour for a time.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They may fall into ſin, whereby the Name of God may be blaſphemed, Religion diſgraced, their Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſorely wounded, the godly much grieved, the wicked extremely hardened in their ſins by their falls.</p>
               <p n="5">5. They may fall into temporal deſtruction, though not into eternal;<note place="margin">Prima eſt haec ultio, quod ſe ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice nemo nocens ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvitur. <hi>Juvenal. Satyr. 13.</hi>
                  </note> they may fall into the correcting hands of God, though not into his revenging hands; they may ſo fall, as that they may be <hi>filii ſub ira,</hi> though not <hi>filii irae,</hi> children under wrath, though not children of wrath. Even the Satyriſt could ſay, This is the firſt revenge which God taketh on a guilty ſoul, that in its own judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the ſin committed is detained till repentance diſmiſs it, and ſo the ſinner is under wrath.</p>
               <p>So then theſe words reach all, both ſeemingly godly, and really godly; him that thinketh he ſtandeth, and he that ſtandeth by grace.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p>THe words being thus cleered, I ſhall only lay down three Points of Doctrine to be handled.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That every Chriſtian ought to have a watchful eye over himſelf, leſt he fall into ſin.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That every one that is a Profeſſor of the Chriſtian Religion is bound to have a watchful eye over himſelf, leſt he fall away.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Every godly man is bound to take heed to himſelf, leſt he fall from grace in any degree.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:59782:7"/>
               <p>For the firſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 1. Every one that is a Chriſtian, and profeſſeth godlineſs, ought to have a watchful eye over himſelf, leſt he fall into ſin. <hi>I ſaid I will take heed to my ways,</hi> ſaith <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 39.1. This was <hi>David</hi>'s reſolved practice. <hi>Take heed to your ſelves, leſt at any time your hearts be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with ſurfetting and drunkenneſs,</hi> Luke 21.34. This charge was given by Chriſt to his Apoſtles: And he ſaid unto them, <hi>Take heed, and beware of covetouſneſs,</hi> Luk. 12.15. In many other places is this preſſed on men as a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervative againſt ſin, by ſuch terms as theſe; Look to your ſelves, Watch, Walk circumſpectly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Reaſons of the Point.</p>
               <p>Great reaſon there is why we ſhould be watchful in this reſpect.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. Becauſe of that propenſity and natural inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that is in us to every ſin: Every mans heart is fraught with the principles and habits of every ſin, his heart is a full treaſure of wickedneſs: We may all ſigh out that doleful complaint of <hi>Paul,</hi> O miſerable men that we are, becauſe of a body of death within us! Do ſome run gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily into drunkenneſs? Do others run greedily into un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs? Do ſome commit fornication? Do ſome tempt Chriſt, and others murmure againſt God? Do ſome run into thoſe <hi>muta peccata,</hi> into unnatural ſins? Thou art na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally prone to act the ſame ſins, yea the greateſt ſins that ever were acted, if thou doſt not take heed and beware of them. Other mens abominable vices are looking-glaſſes wherein we may behold the face of our own hearts and natural inclinations: As face anſwereth face, ſo doth the heart of man anſwer the heart of man. 'Twas an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogant ſpeech of that Phariſee, <hi>God I thank thee, I am not as other men are, nor as this Publican,</hi> ſeeing he had as vile an heart, as unjuſt an heart as yonder Publican. We trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at the thoughts of the ſins which <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> acted, and ever judge them worthy of that place where they are; we are as naturally ſinful as <hi>Cain,</hi> as <hi>Judas,</hi> prone to act
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59782:7"/> the ſame; wherefore we muſt take heed in reſpect of our natural proneneſs, leſt we fall: the ſame weeds will ſpring up in our lives, if we take no heed to pluck up theſe roots of bitterneſs.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe we are ſubject to the ſame temptations as others are; wherefore let us take heed leſt we fall into the ſame ſins into which others do, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1. The ſame fruit with which the Serpent begui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed <hi>Eve,</hi> he ſeduced <hi>Adam.</hi> The Divel can find out a <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> garment, and a gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en wedge to tempt thee, as he did <hi>Acban:</hi> Thirty pieces of ſilver may entice thee to betray Chriſt, as it did <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das: Abel</hi>'s holineſs may be an occaſion to ſtir up malice in thee, as it did in <hi>Cain:</hi> Common experience teſtifieth that all are ſubject to the ſame temptations; were there a general communication about temptations, this would be the general vote, <hi>nemine contradicente,</hi> we are a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l tempted to pride, to luſt, to covetouſneſs, to diſtruſt, to deſpair, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> what ſin is there to which we are not tempted? Every one that hath any experience of Satans malice, and takes any notice of ſinful ſuggeſtions darted by Satan, will ſay with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in himſelf, as <hi>Luther</hi> once ſaid, I think the Divel hath no other work to do but to tempt poor <hi>Luther:</hi> Wherefore take heed leſt ſome temptation or other take you by the heel, as <hi>Jacob</hi> did <hi>Eſau,</hi> and ſupplant you; the leſs heed we take, the more prevalent temptations are; Satans fiery darts will ſoon ſet us on fire of hell, if we do not take heed of him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 3. Becauſe there is a ſnare laid in every thing to entrap us; wherefore let us take heed leſt we fall. Alas for me (ſaith S. <hi>Bernard</hi>) I ſee wars providing for me on every ſide;<note place="margin">Hei mihi, quia undique mihi tela video, undique tela volant, undique tentamenta; undique pericula, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque me vertam! nulla eſt ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas; &amp; quae mulcent, &amp; qua triſtant, omnia timeo. <hi>Bernard. p. 1061.</hi>
                  </note> wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, tentations, dangers flye about me, and aſſail me whereſoever I go! which way ſhall I turn me? There is no ſafe being any where, I am afraid of every thing, of ſuch things as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light me, and of ſuch things alſo as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59782:8"/> moleſt and make me ſad. <hi>Antoninus</hi> dreamed that there were ſnares laid over all the world to entrap him; it was his dream, but there are ſnares really laid in all places to enſnare our ſouls. <hi>In the way wherein I walked,</hi> ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, have they privily laid a ſnare for me;</hi> and in the way and places wherein we are daily walking and travelling do theſe baits lie, they are the things which we continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly look upon, hear of, handle, taſte, feel, and make uſe of. The Divel lays his ſnares in our ſhops, in our houſes, in the fields, in the ſtreets, in every company; he lays ſnares on our tables,<note place="margin">Nemo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis tam periculo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, quam in impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bos pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitas ſua. <hi>Senec. Epiſt. 32.</hi> Meruis longa at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> inſiguis honorum pagina. <hi>Juvenal. Sat. 10.</hi>
                  </note> he lays a ſnare in our gifts, parts, duties, to draw us to pride and hypocriſie; he turns eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtone, that he might make us fall: As S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of himſelf, that he became all things to all men, that he might gain ſome; ſo we may ſay of the Divel, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes all things to all men in his way, that he might gain men to himſelf. The Hiſtorian obſerveth of <hi>Cataline,</hi> that when he began his rebellion, he applied himſelf to every mans humour to draw him into the ſame rebellion; if he ſaw a man covetous, he tempted him with money; if he ſaw a man ambitious, he proffer'd honours, prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and promotions to him to enſnare him. Thus doth Satan; if we are covetous, he hath an <hi>Achan</hi>'s wedge for us; if we be addicted to honour, he can ſhew us all the glory of the world, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 4. Becauſe of the malice of Satan: The Divel hath the greateſt malice againſt the Profeſſors of Piety; therefore he is called their Adverſary; <hi>Your Adverſary the Divel goes about like a roaring Lion,</hi> ſaith <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 Pet. 5.8. The Divel is not called a wicked mans Adverſary, he is called their Father; <hi>Ye are of your Father the Divel,</hi> ſaith Chriſt to the wicked Jews, <hi>John</hi> 8.44. Our Saviour told <hi>Peter, Satan deſireth to winnow thee:</hi> He doth not ſo much deſire to winnow a wicked man; Chriſt ſaith of them, that they will do the works of their Father; they are as willing and forward to ſin, as the Divel is to have them to ſin: A Fiſher-man had rather catch one fiſh then
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59782:8"/> a thouſand frogs; Satan would rather draw a Profeſſor to ſin then a thouſand profane perſons: As <hi>David</hi> ſaid of <hi>Goliah</hi>'s ſword, <hi>There is none like that;</hi> ſo the Divel of the ſins of profeſſing Chriſtians, there is no ſin like theirs; no fall like a Saints fall; no adultery like that of <hi>David;</hi> his adultery was more advantagious to Satan then the blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies of a thouſand <hi>Rabſhekahs:</hi> that as our Saviour ſaith of the converſion of a ſinner, <hi>There is joy in heaven over one ſinner that repenteth, more then over ninety and nine juſt perſons which need no repentance,</hi> Luke 15.7. ſo there is joy in hell, in the preſence of the Divel and his Angels, over the fall of one godly man, more then over the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable practices of ninety and nine profane perſons; for the Divel knoweth, 1. That God is more diſhonoured and more blaſphemed by the fall of one Profeſſor of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, then by ſeven falls of wicked men daily. 2. He knoweth that his fall will bring a greater diſgrace and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credit to Religion; thereby the Goſpel and the godly are evil ſpoken of. 3. He knoweth the falls of godly men (like the fall of <hi>Amaſa</hi> in the mid-way) do hinder people from following after Chriſt, yea it extremely hardens wicked men in their wickedneſs; wherefore he will leave ninety nine profane perſons, to ſeek out one of them to tempt them to ſin: Wherefore O ye Profeſſors of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs take heed leſt he give you a fall; you are all in a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faring condition in the field with an Adverſary, and he no mean one, but a Lion, a roaring Lion, a diligent Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary, who is always going about ſeeking whom he may devour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 5. Becauſe of the deceitfulneſs of all the Enemies of our Salvation: The world is deceitful; the things of the world are deceitful, <hi>Math.</hi> 13.22. riches are called <hi>deceitful riches;</hi> the favour of man is <hi>decitful, Prov.</hi> 31.30. and <hi>Wine is a mocker, Prov.</hi> 30.1. Men are apt to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and mocked by theſe things: Now theſe things are not properly deceitful, they are ſo rather <hi>objective</hi> then <hi>ſubjective:</hi> Man by ſin hath brought a curſe upon the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59782:9"/> and by the judgment of God this curſe is retorted from the creature to man again. Souldiers in their march are ſubject to ambuſcadoes; ſo the creatures do as it were lie in ambuſh to do us a miſchief. And as the things of the world are thus deceitful, ſo are the men of the world very deceitful, labouring to draw us into all manner of ſin; theſe do not only deceive men by falſe hopes, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by ſuggeſting falſe fears. <hi>Severus</hi> terrified the <hi>Roman</hi> Army by clapping head-pieces with lighted matches upon the ſtumps of the trees in the night, making the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of a new formidable Army; and as an Enemy giving an alarum to a City on one ſide, draweth the defendants thither, while the Souldiers are undermining and ſcaling the other: So the world doth many times ſcare men out of their profeſſion, and affright them with dangers from men, to bring them in danger of the real wrath of God. Sin likewiſe is deceitful; and the luſts and works of ſin are deceitful; and your own evil hearts are deceitful a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things, above ſin, Divels, and the world; and all theſe conſpire together to deceive you: what need have we then to have a watchful eye over our ſelves? You will take heed that men cheat you not out of your money, out of your Eſtates and Land; and if you knew you had ſuch perſons about you that would deceive you if you took not heed, you would double your watch. Beloved, let me tell you, theſe deceivers I am now ſpeaking of would deceive you of your ſouls, more worth then the whole world, they would cheat you of an everlaſting In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, of a glorious Kingdom in Heaven; their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign is to deceive you into Hell, and to bring you to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal damnation: Wherefore take heed leſt ye fall.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 6. Becauſe you that profeſs your ſelves to be god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, you have more to loſe then wicked men have to loſe; therefore take heed leſt ye fall: Have wicked men a ſoul to loſe, ſo have you? Have wicked men a Heaven to loſe, ſo have you? Have wicked men a God, a Chriſt to loſe, ſo have you? But you that ſtand have yet more to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59782:9"/> loſe then they; you have communion with God to loſe, which wicked men have not; how will a great fall break your communion with God? you have a Spirit of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and adoption to loſe, which wicked men have not; you have boldneſs of acceſs to the Throne of Grace to loſe, which wicked men have not; you have joy in the Holy Ghoſt, and peace of Conſcience to loſe, which wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men have not: what need then have you to take heed to your ſelves that ye fall not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 7. Becauſe of Gods ſeverity againſt ſin and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. This is the very reaſon of the Apoſtle in my Text; wherefore let him that ſtandeth, take heed leſt he fall: Seeing God plagued Fornicatours, deſtroyed Murmurers, fixed ſuch exemplary marks of his diſpleaſure upon the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> let us take heed leſt we ſin as they, and ſuffer the like puniſhment: If you murmur, he will ſend a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer to deſtroy you; if you murmur againſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> he can make the earth to ſwallow you up; if you fall into fornication, and burn in luſt, he will make fire to burn you, as it did the <hi>Sodomites;</hi> if you harden your hearts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gods threatnings, he will make the waters to drown you, as they did the <hi>Egyptians;</hi> if you luſt after fleſh, he will give you Quails in wrath, and the Plague to boot; if you ſin as <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi> did, he may ſtrike you dead preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: God is always the ſame, as ſevere againſt ſin in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, as againſt ſin in the <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> he will chaſtiſe his own people now under the Goſpel, as he chaſtiſed them under the Law: though hand joyn in hand, yet he will never ſuffer ſin to go unpuniſhed. Remember <hi>Lot</hi>'s wife, how God dealt with her for one act of diſobedience, O ye children of diſobedience! Remember <hi>Corah</hi> and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, O ye murmurers! Remember <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Cozbi,</hi> ye fornicators! Remember <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah,</hi> ye polluters of ſacred things! Remember <hi>Belſhazzar,</hi> O ye ſwiniſh drunkards! Remember the rich Glutton, all ye ſenſual Epicures! Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member <hi>Cain,</hi> all ye perſecuters! Remember <hi>Judas,</hi> all ye covetous profeſſors, leſt their plagues fall upon you, for
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59782:10"/> your falling into their ſins! Do you fear the Plague, then fear Fornication? Do you fear War, then flye Idolatry! Do you fear judgments, then fear ſin? Do you fear to fall into Hell, fear ſin? you need to fear no evil of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if you fear to commit ſin; but if you fear not to fall into ſin, be ſure you ſhall fall into miſery.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. THis may inform us of the great falls and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals among Profeſſors: There are two prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal cauſes;
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Heedleſsneſs,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Self-confidence.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Heedleſsneſs:</hi> Men take no heed to themſelves, nor to their ways, wherefore they ſtumble and fall, and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times wound their Conſciences: Heedleſs children get moſt falls and broken bones; ſo do heedleſs Chriſtians: many of the Lords Worthies have fallen ſhamefully through heedleſsneſs; for want of circumſpection <hi>David</hi> fell into great ſcandal. It is juſt with God to let looſe the Divel upon thoſe who walk looſely: the Divel is ſaid to watch, the main thing he watcheth for, is to find us careleſs and heedleſs, then we become a prey to him: The ſlumbering of the Sentinel giveth advantage to the Enemy; when the Guard is in a deep ſleep, the City is ſoon ſurprized: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a precious ſoul hath the Divel ſurprized and devoured, finding them aſleep, taking no heed to themſelves.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Self-confidence:</hi> When men preſume upon their own ſtrength, or preſume that they ſhall not fall into ſuch or ſuch a ſin, they do not find inclinations to it; they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume they hate it ſo, as that they ſhall never be overtaken with it; like <hi>Hazael</hi> hearing what cruelties he ſhould act upon the women and infants, ſaid to the Prophet, <hi>Is thy ſervant a dog,</hi> that he ſhould do ſuch deteſtable things? as if he ſhould have ſaid, I hate the mention of ſuch ſins,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59782:10"/> the naming of ſuch cruelties: So it is with many a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, hearing of the grievous falls of others into ſin, they think they abhor ſuch courſes, and though others commit ſuch ſins, they ſhould not. It was <hi>Peter</hi>'s caſe when our Saviour told him he ſhould deny him, he abhorred the naming of it, being confident of himſelf, though all the reſt of Chriſts Diſciples and others ſhould deny him, yet he ſhould not, he loved Chriſt too well to deny him; his ſelf-confidence ſupplanted him, and gave him that fearful fall.</p>
               <p n="1">1. God puniſheth ſelf-confidence with ſubtraction of his grace; ſeeing the child will go alone, let him go alone.</p>
               <p n="2">2. God puts them out of his protection, by giving ſuch up to ſome ſtrong temptation, that they may fall; and that for theſe ends.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That Chriſtians may ſee their own weakneſs, that they are as unſtable as waters; if they are not bank'd in with divine grace, their corruptions will ſoon run abroad: the imperfection of our ſanctification cauſeth weakneſs, as young tender Plants are weak and bowed every way.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That by their falls they may learn to take more heed: A burnt child will dread the fire; a wounded con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience will make a Chriſtian more circumſpect; ſin work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth good in the godly <hi>occaſionaliter,</hi> occaſionally, though not <hi>cauſative,</hi> cauſatively; <hi>Quia inde redeunt cautiores, humiliores,</hi> becauſe they go out from ſin more cautious, and more humble, ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. That God may have more of their company, and of their dependence upon him: Children after they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſome hurt by a fall, will keep cloſe to their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſide, and will have them to hold them, leſt they fall again: God is then more ſought unto from his people for ſupporting grace; God hath more of their dependence on him, leſt they fall again into the like ſins.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:59782:11"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. BE exhorted to take heed to your ſelves; <hi>Walk circumſpectly, Eph.</hi> 5.15. Such as travel in ſlippery paths, or ways troubleſom to be found, are care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to look to their feet, to obſerve their marks and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; ſo muſt it be with him that wil travel ſafely through the ſlippery and dangerous way of this worlds wilderneſs ſaith a good Divine of ours.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> A man that walketh over a narrow bridge in fear, walketh <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, exactly, circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectly, his eye is on his feet, leſt he ſtep aſide and fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the river. <hi>Ponder the paths of thy feet,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon, that thy ways may all be ordered aright, Prov.</hi> 4.26. Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpection is a Chriſtian Life-guard; it makes a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian like that Beaſt in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> full of eyes within and without; eyes without, to make him to look to his ways, that he fall not; eyes within, to make him to take heed to his heart, that he be not deceived: A Chriſtian is then in his watch-tower, when he walketh circumſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; that man walketh moſt ſurely, that walketh moſt tremblingly: <hi>Bleſſed is the man that feareth always. Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus gradus certitudinis, quantus gradus ſollicitudinis.</hi> Do you fear judgments? do you fear to be deſtroyed of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer? do you fear the arrows of divine vengeance? then fear ſin: you need not fear judgments if you fear ſin: he that takes heed of falling into ſin, doth in that take heed of falling into miſery; he feareth Hell moſt, that is moſt afraid of ſin. Should any put out this queſtion, what ſhall I do that I may avoid judgments? the beſt anſwer is, take heed that ye fall not; for if ye ſin, be ſure your ſin will find you out; if you fall into ſin, you ſhall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly fall into the hands of the living God. I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhew you,
<q>
                     <l>Of what we muſt take heed;</l>
                     <l>To what we muſt take heed.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:59782:11"/>1. Of what we muſt take heed.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Take heed of all ſinful occaſions: <hi>Occaſio facit fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem,</hi> opportunity makes a thief; many a man is overtaken with a ſin, being firſt overtaken with an opportunity; the argument which the Harlot uſed to entice the young man was, now is an opportunity, <hi>Prov.</hi> 7.19. <hi>Come let us take our fill of love, for the good man is not at home, he is gone a long journey.</hi> So <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Miſtreſs uſeth the ſame argument; <hi>When Joſeph went into the houſe to do his buſineſs, and there were none of the men of the houſe there within, ſhe caught him by the garment, ſaying, Lye with me,</hi> Geneſ. 39.11, 12. It is a note of a wicked man to wait for opportunities of ſinning: <hi>The Adulterer waiteth for the twilight,</hi> ſaith <hi>Job.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Take heed of the firſt riſe of ſin, a ſinful motion, a ſinful thought; take theſe helliſh brats, and daſh their brains againſt the ſtones: <hi>Magna vis in minimis,</hi> there is great force in the ſmalleſt things; a ſpark of fire hath burnt an houſe to the ground; a flaſh of lightening (which vaniſheth in a moment) hath done the like: As <hi>Sampſon</hi> ſaid of the jaw-bone with which he ſlew a thouſand <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines,</hi> with the jaw-bone of an Aſs (a poor inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable engine for war) have I ſlain heaps upon heaps; ſo the Divel by a ſinful thought, by a ſinful motion hath ſlain multitudes of men.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Take heed of making a parley with a temptation; it is not ſafe to play with the edged tools of Hell: <hi>Eve</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained conference with the Serpent about the fruit wherewith he tempted her, and Gods threatnings, and we feel the ſmart of her fall to this day. Temptations to ſin are to be reſiſted, not to be debated upon; we have a promiſe, if we reſiſt the Divel, he ſhall flye from us; if we are afraid of the temptation that aſſaileth us, we ſhall be angry againſt it, and ſhew our anger in making a quick reſiſtance againſt it, and ſo prevent or expell the ſin ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Take heed of tempting company; <hi>Peter</hi>'s being in the High-Prieſts Hall was the occaſion of his ſad fall. He
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59782:12"/> that findeth and feareth his proneneſs to any ſin,<note place="margin">Quid tibi neceſſe eſt in ea ver ſari domo, in qua ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe eſt quotidie aut perire aut vince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. <hi>Hier. Ep. 47. de ſuſpect. contuber.</hi>
                  </note> whether gluttony, drunkenneſs, uncleanneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> muſt keep out of vicious company, and occaſions leading to thoſe ſins, and reſolve with <hi>David</hi> to flye whatſoever may draw him thereunto, and ſay with <hi>David, Away from me ye wicked, for I will keep the Commandments of my God,</hi> Pſal. 119. Tempting company puts a man upon a neceſſity either of periſhing or conquering: So S. <hi>Hierom</hi> intimateth; Why muſt you needs live in that houſe, in which you muſt needs either periſh or vanquiſh every day? A circumſpect Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is loth to be put to either.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Take heed of the leaſt act of ſin: It is notable what a Learned man ſaith; They are effects of former ſins, and cauſes of the latter, and that not only by Gods juſt judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment permitting it ſo, but alſo by coherence and affinity: one ſin brings on another, a leſſer draws on a greater, as leſſer ſticks do ſet the greater on fire: a little Thief put in at a window, ſets open the doors to let in the greater: in the body of man frequent labours though but little, beget an aptitude to endure greater: a little rent in a garment makes it fit to receive a wider, every nail and thorn is apt to take hold of it, and to make the rent broader. <hi>Qui mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma contemnit, paulatim decidit,</hi> he that takes no heed of leſſer ſins, falls by degrees into greater abſurdities: I think that more go to Hell for ſmaller ſins, then for great ones: leſſer ſins perſiſted in, provoke the Divel to aſſault us with ſtronger temptations; as a maids eaſie yielding to ſome leſſer toyings provokes the Wanton to tempt her to greater indecencies: <hi>The beginnings of ſin</hi> (ſaith a Learned man) <hi>are modeſt;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Principia peccati mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſta ſunt.</note> Satan tempts us but to ſmall matters at firſt, but if he find us give way to him therein, then (like bold beggars) he ſets upon us for greater courteſies: Men are more apt to commit leſſer ſins then greater; for if a man fall into a great ſin, 1. It is always in his fight, it ſtares him in the face; his Conſcience often bites and ſtings him for it:<note place="margin">Medica ſunt qua perdunt.</note> and 2. Leſſer ſins are often committed, and quickly forgotten; therefore they are ſmall ſins that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59782:12"/> moſt men. Therefore let me tell thoſe that think their caſe well, if they can be taxed but for one or two ſins, and being told of it, they anſwer it is all their fault, That as ſmall ſins deſtroy, ſo will a few ſmall ones; one knife in thy throat is enough to diſpatch thee; one bullet in thy guts will kill thee; and one ſin in thy heart is enough to deſtroy thee.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To what we muſt take heed.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Take heed to your heart: <hi>In all thy keepings keep thy heart; Prov.</hi> 4.23. he only that knoweth the ſinfulneſs and deceitfulneſs of the heart, ſaith <hi>it is deceitful above all things:</hi> Men are deceitful, ſin is deceitful, the Divel is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful, but there's no ſuch deceitfulneſs in them as is in our hearts; every one of us carrieth his own ſupplanter within his breaſt. Be ſure to keep ſin out of your hearts; if Satan can get and keep poſſeſſion of our hearts, he hath won the main fort of the ſoul; no part of man can ſin without the heart, the heart can ſin without all the reſt: the Fox goeth to the flock purpoſing to devour a Lamb, and is prevented by the vigilance of the Shepherd, yet <hi>vulpes exit, vulpes egreditur,</hi> he goes forth a Fox, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth home a Fox: the heart intendeth a ſin which is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver brought into action, yet it ſinneth in that intention; <hi>He that looks upon a woman to luſt after her,</hi> ſaith our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>hath committed adultery in his heart,</hi> Math. 5. The heart is like a Mill, if the wind or water be violent, the Mill will go whether the Miller will or no, yet he may chuſe what kind of grain it ſhall grind; if the affections be ſtrong and violent, the heart will be working: Be ſure to keep ſin out of your hearts, and ſuffer not one known ſin willingly to root there. It is ſaid of <hi>Creta,</hi> that no ſerpent nor venemous thing will live there, but dye as ſoon as it cometh into that Iſland, ſuch an antipathy there is between them and the nature of that ſoil; ſo let us be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected toward ſin, let us labour to keep it out of our hearts, knowing that a bad gueſt is more eaſily kept out, then thruſt out of doors; but if we cannot do that, let
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:59782:13"/> us labour to ſmother and ſtiffle it as ſoon as it cometh there.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Take heed to your affections: It is the Wiſemans advice, <hi>When ye go into the Houſe of God, take heed to your feet,</hi> Eccleſ. 5.1. take heed to your feet whereſoever you go; if a man hath a love to ſin, he will fall into ſin when opportunity ſerveth: the affections are the feet of the ſoul, ſee that your affections be ordered according to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of faith ſincerely and conſtantly, cleaving to all good in an holy order, and ſhunning all evils in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral kinds and degrees, as they are diſcovered to be evil by the power of faith judging according to the word of truth: ſee that your affections be moved by ſound reaſons, cleerly apprehended, then you will not love what you ſhould hate; let your affections keep within the pale of ſound Reaſon, and move according to her information; it is very dangerous to give way to looſe affections, if once they have broken the bands of reaſon, they will hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry us up and down into many inconveniences.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Take heed to your outward ſenſes, eſpecially the ear and the eye: <hi>Greg. Nazianzen</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Greg. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ianz.</note> ſaid, <hi>That if a man would live in the world, he muſt have a vail on his eyes, a lock on his ears, and a compaſs on his lips:</hi> If theſe two ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes be not watched, they will be like <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in evil: the ſenſes are the out-works; if Satan once take the out-works, he will quickly maſter the fort within.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Take heed to your ears; do not liſten to the voice of helliſh charmers charming never ſo ſweetly; corrupt communication, <hi>dum aurem afficit, animam interficit,</hi> while it affects and pleaſeth the ear, it killeth the ſoul. <hi>Joſeph</hi> would not hearken to the ſollicitations of his wanton Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, though ſhe ſpake to him day by day, <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.10.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Take heed to your eyes, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.26. <hi>David</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>Turn away mine eyes from beholding vanity, Pſal.</hi> 119. The firſt ſin that ever was committed, entred in by the eye, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.6. Phyſitians obſerve; that death firſt ſeizeth on the eyes, becauſe ſin firſt ſeized on them; at theſe win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:59782:13"/> moſt ſins creep into our ſouls; looking begets li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the heart; therefore it is not good to look where we may not like. The <hi>Romans</hi> did ill provide for the keeping the Law which they made, that Virgins ſhould drink no wine, when they permitted them to ſee it; <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi>'s wiſdom exceeded theirs, when to a man that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth wine well, and is apt to be enſnared by it, he giveth counſel, <hi>not to look upon it, when it giveth its colour in the cup, and moveth it ſelf aright,</hi> Prov. 23.31.<note place="margin">Et licet quidam pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris eſſe vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutis prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentem contemne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re volupta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, tamen ego arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tror ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioris eſſe continen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, neſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re quod quaeras. <hi>Hier. Ep. ad Laetam. Caſſian inſtitut. lib. 5. c 32.</hi>
                  </note> So <hi>Hierom</hi> in one of his Epiſtles to <hi>Laeta,</hi> where he giveth direction how to bring up her daughter virtuouſly, among other things adviſeth her not to ſuffer her daughter to ſee thoſe meats, which ſeeing ſhe might be moved to deſire; and this his advice he ſhuts up with theſe words: <hi>Though ſome there be who think it a point of greater virtue to contemn a pleaſure when it is preſent, yet I judge it to be a thing of more ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, not to know or ſee that thing which one may not ſafely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire. Caſſian</hi> alſo reporteth of a certain young man, that after he had left the world many years, and betook him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to a Monaſtery, having received a packet of Letters from his father and mother, and divers of his dear friends, he durſt not look upon them, but threw them all into the fire with theſe words; <hi>Ite cogitationes patriae, pariter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cremamini, nè me ulterius ad illa quae fugi, vocare tentetis;</hi> Be gone ye thoughts of my Country, and burn for compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, for fear leſt ye tempt me to look again toward the things which I have forſaken: He feared (ſaith the ſtory) leſt by the reading of their lines, and the ſight of their names, he ſhould have been enticed to warp toward their company and the world again. The eye before the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> was the window to let in good inſtructions into the ſoul, but ſince the fall it is <hi>Proxeneta peccati,</hi> the Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker that goes betwixt the heart and the object to make up the ſinful bargain.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:59782:14"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <p>I Now come to the ſecond point of Doctrine, and note from my Text,</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Obſerv.</note>That it concerns all who profeſs godlineſs to take heed to themſelves leſt they fall away from their profeſſion. The Apoſtle principally aimeth at Profeſſors in this his Caution; <hi>He that thinketh he ſtandeth,</hi> that is,</p>
               <p n="1">1. He that conceiteth himſelf to be in the ſtate of grace.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He that conceiteth he ſhall perſevere to the end, that thinks within himſelf, he ſhall (as <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks of the Sun) rejoyce like a giant to run the courſe of Chriſtianity.</p>
               <p>For explication obſerve theſe diſtinctions: there is a twofold falling away,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Partial,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Total.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Diſtin. </seg>1</label> 1. Partial; when a Profeſſor falls from degrees of his holy profeſſion; there is love in him ſtill, but there is not his firſt love; there is zeal in him ſtill, but there is not the firſt zeal; he takes more liberty then formerly, walks in a broader way, removeth the ancient bounds of godlineſs. I ſhall ſpeak of this in the laſt Doctrine.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Total falling away; and this is when a man caſteth off the yoke of Chriſt, and puts his neck under the yoke of <hi>Belial,</hi> ſhakes hands with his profeſſion, and embraceth profaneneſs, or as <hi>Demas</hi> ſhook hands with Chriſt, and embraced this preſent world; or falls from the ſhew of godlineſs into an open ſhew of profaneneſs, takes no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to ſit with <hi>Mary</hi> at the feet of Chriſt, but loveth to fit in the ſeat of the ſcornful.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Diſtin. </seg>2</label> Total falling away is twofold,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Temporary,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Final.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Temporary, for a time; when men depart from
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:59782:14"/> God and Chriſt, as <hi>Noah</hi>'s Dove went from the Ark, who having tyred her ſelf abroad, and finding no reſting place for the ſoles of her feet, returned again to the Ark: Thus many a Profeſſor falls off from God and his ways, flut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters up and down in the world, but finds no peace in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, no content in the ways of ſin, returns to God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: Such was the falling away of <hi>Solomon,</hi> who did for a while caſt off God, fall into the fond and inordinate love of women, and inſatiably too, of many women; he had ſeven hundred wives, and three hundred concubines, 1 <hi>Reg.</hi> 11.1.3. and that which was worſe, into the love of ſtrange women, <hi>idolaters,</hi> of whom the Lord had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a charge to <hi>Iſrael, Ye ſhall not go in unto them, neither ſhall they go in to you:</hi> and to outward incontinency he added ſpiritual adultery; his wives turned away his heart from God, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. he fell to idolatry, and followed after ſtrange gods, erected Temples to the Idols which his wives adored, ſet up Altars, Ornaments, Prieſts, and all upon Mount <hi>Olivet,</hi> before the face of the Lord in his Temple, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 23.13. he gave himſelf to all pleaſures and vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties under the Sun (as appeareth by his book of <hi>Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes,</hi> which he wrote after his return), but could find no contentment in all, nor in any thing under the Sun; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſee what he ſaith, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.13. here is the <hi>ſumma to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talis, totum officii, totum conatus, totum faelicitatis;</hi> the whole duty, the whole endeavour, the whole happineſs of man. This was <hi>Iſraels</hi> revolt, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.7. and ſome Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines conceive, that <hi>Demas</hi> thus fell away for a time, and returned again.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Final falling; to fall irrecoverably, to caſt off God and his ways for ever; when men go from God and his ways, as <hi>Noah</hi>'s Raven went from the Ark, that fled away and never return'd again. The word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> frequently uſed in Scripture, ſignifieth to depart from that which we formerly ſtood to; it is a military word; for among Souldiers ſuch a one was anciently called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> transfuga.</note> 
                  <hi>qui or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem ſuum &amp; locum in acie datum turpiter deſeruit,</hi> that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:59782:15"/> baſely deſerted his place and rank aſſigned him in the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, <hi>vel qui ad hoſtes transfugit,</hi> who fled away to the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: Such a one then is an Apoſtate, who falls away and departs from that faith he formerly ſtood to and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, and becometh the ſervant of ſin, and the vaſſal of Satan. This is called in Scripture, <hi>a turning away from following the Lord, Pſal.</hi> 125.5. Sound Chriſtians, like <hi>Caleb, follow the Lord fully,</hi> but the unſound Chriſtian turneth away from following of him. It is likewiſe called, <hi>a leaving the paths of righteouſneſs,</hi> Prov. 2.13. <hi>a going backwards,</hi> and not forwards, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 7.14. it is called <hi>a departing from the faith,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.1. when a man doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight to the Spirit of grace, flings away the ſtrictneſs of holy walking, caſts off the yoke of Chriſt, and turneth the grace of God into laſciviouſneſs, this is a woful apoſtacy; this is that which the Apoſtle meant in <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.6. where he uſeth the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which ſignifieth the fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of reprobates, as learned <hi>Zanchy</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zanch. in Heb. 6 6.</note> noteth, ſuch who ſtumble and fall, and never riſe more, who never ſtay till they fall headlong into everlaſting deſtruction: This was the fall of <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> of whom the Apoſtle ſaith, they made ſhipwrack of their faith and of a good conſcience; it is impoſſible to recover a Ship once daſht into pieces running upon a rock, and the Apoſtle ſaith of ſuch, it is impoſſible for them to repent.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Diſtin. </seg>3</label> This total and final Apoſtacy is twofold.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Open and notorious; a falling from open profeſſion into open profaneneſs; a falling from open profeſſion into open oppoſition of the ways of God: Thus <hi>Alexander</hi> the Copper-ſmith fell away and oppoſed <hi>Paul</hi>'s preaching, which was worſe then to withſtand his perſon; doctrinal oppoſition is far worſe then perſonal. Great was the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy of <hi>Bolſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cus,</hi> whom the Papiſts afterward hired to write <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Life, where ſo many lines, ſo many lies. <hi>Baldwin,</hi> another Apoſtate, changed his Religion at leaſt 3 or 4 times for advantage. <hi>Petrus Carolus</hi> was alſo an odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Apoſtate, and troubler of the Church. What a noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59782:15"/> Turn-coat was <hi>Ecebolius,</hi> who under the Emperour <hi>Conſtans</hi> was a zealous Chriſtian, under <hi>Julian</hi> again a bitter Pagan; but when <hi>Julian</hi> was dead, and Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity reſtored, he returns to Chriſtianity again!</p>
               <p n="2">2. There is leſs open, and a not ſo notoriouſly ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous falling away; ſuch as theſe are ſtill Swine, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the mire, and wallow in it without much noiſe; they backſlide in heart from God: Some Profeſſors fall like Stars from the Firmament, all take notice of them; others go out like a candle put under a buſhel, little ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved: Oh take heed of falling from God in any of theſe kinds!</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Reaſons why we ſhould take heed of falling away from the profeſſion of godlineſs.</head>
               <p>THe Reaſons why we ſhould take heed of falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the profeſſion of piety are drawn, 1. From the ſinfulneſs of this ſin. 2. From the diſhonour which is caſt on God. 3. From the judgments following upon it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. From the nature of this ſin; there is that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs in this ſin which is not in other ſins, which will appear in theſe enſuing particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is <hi>magis directè deordinativum à Deo,</hi> as the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſpeak; every ſin is an averſion and deordination from God to the creature, but this is more directly deor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate, and there is this difference; other ſins are a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting from God <hi>in obliq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> â lineâ,</hi> rather going aſide from God, then going away from him, going in a wrong way, then going in a contrary way; but to fall from God is a going from God <hi>in directâ lineâ,</hi> going in a contrary way againſt God, turning the back upon God, Chriſt, Holineſs, Heaven, and their faces directly to the world,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59782:16"/> to their luſts, to hell; like the Moon, after ſhe hath been in conjuction with the Sun, goeth backward till ſhe be in a diametrical oppoſition; or, to uſe that familiar com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of ſome Divines, other ſins are like the wandrings and runnings of a dog from his Maſter after every bird, and after every ſheep he ſees in the field, and then returns to follow his Maſter again; but this ſin of falling away from God, is like the dog which goes with his Maſter ſome way from home, and then leaves him and returns back homeward as faſt as he can again: therefore ſee how God complaineth of this ſin, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 2.13. <hi>My people have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted two evils; they have forſaken me, and gone</hi> to the creature; he accounts it two great evils; drunkenneſs, adultery, and ſuch like, is but one ſingle iniquity, but to depart from God is double iniquity, 'tis two evils.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is the fundamental breach of the Covenant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and man, ſo other ſins are not; it is as the ſin of adultery, which is the breach of the Matrimonial Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; all other unkind paſſages betwixt man and wife are not breaches of it, but only of their promiſe of love and obedience; but adultery is the divorcing ſin, it breaks the knot which nothing can untie but death: ſo it is here; other ſins are againſt our duty, and the engagement of our obedience to God; but to fall away from God is a reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God, and of Chriſt for our God; you do <hi>ipſo facto</hi> ſay in effect, that God ſhall not be your God, and Chriſt ſhall not be your husband; and God again replieth, <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ammi, Loruchamah,</hi> ye are not my people, and I will not be your God, I will not have mercy upon you, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 1.6.9.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is <hi>diſpoſitivum ad deteriora;</hi> when a man is acting this ſin, the Divel hath him on an high pinacle, from whence he tumbleth headlong into any ſin; ſuch a man falls from hypocriſie into open profaneneſs, from open pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſs into Atheiſm, from that into oppoſition of all that is of God; as the Oratour ſaid of ſome, <hi>à bonis ad mala, à malis ad vitia, à vitiis ad deteriora;</hi> ſo theſe men fall from negligence in performances unto a willing neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:59782:16"/> from neglect into wilful contempt, from contempt into hatred, from hatred into oppoſition: <hi>Saul</hi> was firſt an Apoſtate, then a Perſecuter; <hi>Judas</hi> firſt an Hypocrite, then a Traitor: What Biſhop <hi>Latimer</hi> called the ſin of covetouſneſs, we may call this ſin of falling away, <hi>viz. ſcalam inferni,</hi> a ladder by which men go down ſtep by ſtep to the bottom of perdition and deſtruction.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It hath <hi>nullum motivum ad poenitentiam,</hi> no motive to repentance, 'tis the School-mens phraſe; it ſhuts men up in impenitency and final hardneſs, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.6. and the reaſon is, becauſe falling from God is an ejection of the Spirit of grace, and when the Spirit ceaſeth from his ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration on the heart of ſuch a man, it is impoſſible then for him to repent; it is ſaid ſo of no ſin but this: a Profeſſor may fall into a groſs moral vice, as into drunkenneſs, and be renewed again by repentance; he may through weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs deny Chriſt, as <hi>Peter</hi> did, and yet be renewed again by repentance: there is no ſin but this, but a man falling into it may be renewed again by repentance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2. A Second Reaſon is drawn from the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the great diſhonour which is caſt on God, on Chriſt, on all the ways of God. 1. On God, as if he were not a good God to enjoy, a good Maſter to ſerve, as if there were no profit in ſerving the Almighty, or that there were more profit in ſerving baſe luſts, then in ſerving God: See how God complaineth of ſuch, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.5. Thus ſaith the Lord, <hi>What iniquity have your fathers found in me, that they are gone far from me?</hi> So God may ſay to ſuch revolters, you think that I am an unjuſt God, that I have not ſhewn my ſelf ready to do you good, that I am an hard Maſter, exacting, like <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> performance of your tasks, and pay you no wages: what all ye that ye fall off from me? declare if there be any iniquity in me:
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:59782:17"/> what am I a barren wilderneſs, a broken ciſtern, that ye go far from me?<note place="margin">Aquinas.</note> ſhew me what fault is in me. <hi>Aquinas</hi> gives 3 reaſons why men forſake a preſent enjoyment for another: 1. Either it is becauſe it is <hi>majoris boni impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivum,</hi> becauſe it hinders a man from the enjoyment of a greater good, therefore he forſakes it; or, 2. Becauſe it is <hi>faſtidioſum,</hi> it is loathſom and diſreliſhing; or, 3. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it proves <hi>minus delectabile, &amp; minus utile,</hi> leſs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful, and leſs profitable. When men fall away from God, they charge God with all theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They look upon him as an hinderer of a greater good; the pleaſures of ſin, the profits of the world are greater good things to them then God is, while they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him they cannot enjoy theſe things, therefore they caſt off God to embrace this preſent world.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They charge God to be a loathſom God, unworthy of their love, ſervice, and enjoyment, therefore they caſt him off.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They charge God not to be ſo uſeful, ſo good, ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary as he is. Is it not a diſhonour that baſe creatures ſhould caſt off their Lord and Creatour, as if he were unworthy of their ſervice?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Fallers away caſt inſufferable contempt and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour on the Lord that bought them: the Apoſtle ſaith of ſuch, that <hi>they tread under foot the Son of God,</hi> Heb. 10.29. a ſin beyond the ſin of <hi>Judas</hi> who betrayed him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the ſin of <hi>Pilate</hi> who condemned him, beyond the ſin of the Souldiers who crucified and pierced him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the ſin of the Jews who mocked him, they offered not ſuch contempt to him as to tread him under their feet: The phraſe alludeth to our cuſtom; things which we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and abhor, we caſt them under our feet and trample upon them; thus theſe men caſt away Chriſt as if he were the off-ſcouring of the world. When <hi>Pompey</hi>'s Souldiers made a mutiny againſt him for reſtraining them from go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a certain place they deſired to go to, and were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to go in ſpite of him; when no perſwaſions could
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59782:17"/> prevail, but go they would, he laid himſelf down on the ground, ſpeaking thus unto them; If ye will go, then tread on me your Emperour and General: So Chriſt ſaith to backſliders, will ye go away from me? then tread on me your Saviour, trample on this body of mine that was broken for you, reject the blood of the Covenant as an unholy thing, and do deſpite to the Spirit of grace, that is, offer injurious rebellions againſt his motion on your hearts, againſt his holy gifts and workings; ſuch men do interpretatively ſay to the Spirit of grace, Let me alone, I am joyned to the world, and I will be joyned; let me alone, move no more upon the face of my heart, depart and take thy gifts with thee; for I will have my will, I will fulfill my luſts.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They bring an ill report on Chriſtianity it ſelf, on Religion, on all the Ordinances, as if there were no good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in Religion, no pleaſantneſs in the ways of God, no excellency or efficacy in his Ordinances; and by this their falling off harden the hearts of men againſt the ways of God, againſt Religion and the Profeſſors of it.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoord,</hi> Serm. in Eph. 4.30.</note> The He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews call the Winter <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> becauſe it is a reproach, either <hi>actively</hi> to the earth, as if it had no fructifying power in it, and to the other Seaſons of the Year, as if they were all like to the Winter; or <hi>paſſively</hi> to it ſelf, becauſe it is a time, by reaſon of the ſad face of it, the ceſſation of the fruitfulneſs of the earth, leaves, bloſſoms, and comelineſs of trees, and of the warmth of the Sun, that is evil ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of. It is a name that befits a backſliding Chriſtian, he is a reproach to the Ordinances of God, as if they had no quickening and fructifying virtue in them; he is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to all his Society, as if all Chriſtians were like himſelf; and he is a great ſtumbling-block to others, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in Hell take their damnation upon it, that the falling off of a Profeſſor from the ways of God, was the ſtumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling-ſtone at which they ſtumbled and fell into Hell. <hi>Math.</hi> 18.7. <hi>Wo to the man by whom the offence cometh.</hi> The greateſt offence that falls out in the world is the fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59782:18"/> away from the profeſſion; it is a ſcandal with a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, it is <hi>ſcandalum magnatum,</hi> of God, of Saints, of the Goſpel, of godlineſs. <hi>Wo to the world becauſe of offences.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe their falling away is the great ſtumbling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>block, that rock of offence at which the world of wicked men ſtumble and fall eternally into deſtruction; they make men doubt whether that way of profeſſion which they took up, be a good and ſafe way or not; hereupon many grow reſolute to continue in their wicked and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly life, rather then to receive that faith, or walk by thoſe rules of life which ſuch backſliders make profeſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n of. <hi>Salvian</hi> in his time doth often aggravate the ſins of Chriſtians on this very ground: It can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid (ſaith he) of the Gentiles,<note place="margin">Non poteſt dici de Gentib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, Evangelia legunt, &amp; impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dici ſunt, Apoſtolos audiunt, &amp; inebriantur, Chriſtum ſequuntur &amp; rapiunt, vitam improbam agunt, &amp; probam Legem ſe habere dicunt. In nobis igitur Chriſtus patitur opprobrium, in nobis patitur Lex Chriſtiana maledictum. Vide Chriſtianos, quid agunt, &amp; evidenter poteſt de ipſo Christo ſciri, quid loceat. <hi>Salvian, lib. 4. p. 139.</hi>
                  </note> they read the Goſpels and are unchaſt, they hear the Apoſtles and are drunk, they follow Chriſt and plunder, they lead a wicked life, and have a good Law, as they ſay: but it may be ſaid of us: well, what of this? he tells us; In us therefore doth Chriſt ſuffer reproach, in us doth the Chriſtian Law endure ſome diſgrace; for they ſay of us, Lo what manner of men they be that worſhip Chriſt it is falſe, that they have a good Law, as they ſay they have; for if they learned good things, they would undoubtedly be good perſons; ſuch is the Sect, as are the Sectators and Followers of it. And a little after he brings in the Pagans thus ſpeaking: Look upon the Chriſtians, ſee what they do, and by that you may eaſily know what their Chriſt teacheth. But why do they charge us Chriſtians and our God thus? he anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; Why? only for their ſakes who are called Chriſtians, but are not, who by their flagitious and filthy lives do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame the Chriſtian name. By theſe ſpeeches we may col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect how ill the bad lives of Chriſtians made Pagans judge of the way of Chriſtianity; and conſequently, what a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:59782:18"/> blemiſh the evil converſation of Profeſſors may occaſional<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly caſt upon their profeſſion, though never ſo pure and glorious in it ſelf: But wo to the man by whom theſe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences come.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe not only the guilt of his own falling away, but the damnation of others will lye upon him alſo, as a milſtone to ſink him down to the bottom of Hell.<note place="margin">Vide <hi>Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin's</hi> Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph. of <hi>America.</hi>
                  </note> I have read a ſtory of <hi>Hathvey,</hi> an <hi>Indian</hi> Nobleman, who by the cruelties and inſolencies of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> of which his miſerable Country had woful experience, was ſo much prejudiced againſt the Chriſtian Religion,<note place="margin">Barthol. Caſſ. Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Ind.</note> that he refuſed to be baptized: They perſwaded him by many arguments to become a Chriſtian: He demanded firſt, what place was appointed after this life for ſuch as were baptized; an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer was made, Heaven and its joys: ſecondly, what place they that were not baptized ſhould go unto; it was anſwered, to Hell and its torments: thirdly he asked, which of theſe places was appointed for the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> anſwer being made that Heaven was, he reſolved againſt his intended Baptiſm, proteſting, that he had rather go to Hell with the unbaptized, then to Heaven with ſo cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el a people. Whoſoever ſinneth greatly (ſaith <hi>Salvian</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Salvian.</note>) without the offence of others, doth purchaſe damnation only to himſelf; but he that cauſeth others to blaſpheme, caſteth very many together with himſelf into deſtruction. Wicked men have little cauſe to ſcoff at ſuch men, and at Religion for their ſakes, becauſe their falls are a wo to them alſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 3. IN reſpect of your ſelves you ought to take heed of falling away; in divers reſpects.</p>
               <p n="1">1. All the good that ever you did in your lives will prove loſt labour if you fall away; all your faſtings, prayings, hearing of Sermons, humiliations, all your zeal
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59782:19"/> and forwardneſs, all your righteouſneſs ſhall be forgotten, as if you had never done any holy duty or ſervice at all, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.24. for as it is ſaid of a backſlider returning home again, <hi>ver.</hi> 22. that all his tranſgreſſions which he had before committed ſhall not be mentioned; ſo when a Profeſſor turneth away from his righteouſneſs, all his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer righteouſneſs ſhall not be remembred; God will look on that man as if he had never prayed, nor done any good duty at all.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If you fall away, all the good you have done ſhall be an aggravation of your deſtruction, of your torments in Hell; all thy prayers, all thy faſtings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhall be as ſo many piles of wood to encreaſe the fire of Hell; all the Sermons thou haſt heard ſhall heat Hell ſeven times hotter for thee then others; thy profeſſion lifted thee up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, it ſhall then caſt thee down to the loweſt Hell. Tell me, O ye tormenting Divels, ye that are the keepers of Gods houſe of eternal correction and vengeance, hath not the Judge of all the world expreſſed in his Warran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, that when as the petty drunkards and other profane perſons are to be laſhed but with whips only, that you ſhall laſh <hi>Judas</hi> and <hi>Demas</hi> with ſcorpions?</p>
               <p n="3">3. If you fall away, God will never take any pleaſure in you more: It is no leſs then treaſon for a Subject to withdraw his allegiance from his Prince, and become a ſervant to his Enemy; and it is high treaſon againſt Chriſt to fall from him, and become a ſervant to his Enemy, it makes God to abhor him: <hi>If any man draw back, my ſoul ſhall have no pleaſure in him,</hi> Heb. 10.38. The husband may bear much with the froward humours of his wife, while ſhe is chaſt and ſincere; but if ſhe withdraw from him, and follow after other Lovers, he cannot endure it. God takes no delight either in the perſons or ſervices of Apoſtates, whatſoever duties are done by them in their declining eſtate the Lord abhorreth; he takes delight in his Spouſe that keeps cloſe to him, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.14. <hi>O my Dove,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>let me ſee thy countenance; ſweet is thy voice, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59782:19"/> thy face is comely:</hi> but God heareth not the prayers, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeth not the ſervices of ſuch ſinners as theſe are, if any be performed by them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A ſpiritual curſe from God commonly ſeizeth on Apoſtates, which (as the waters of jealouſie under the Law given to ſuſpected women, made their bellies to rot, ſo this curſe upon Apoſtates) will make their gifts, parts, ſeeming graces to rot; an Apoſtate (like <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zars</hi> image) degenerateth from an head of gold and breaſt of ſilver, into feet of iron and clay: when a man keeps cloſe to God, he bleſſeth that little that he hath, and it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth into a great ſtock; but when a man departs from God, he is like a ſieve that can hold no water, or like a golden cup with an hole in the bottom: as the tree which our Saviour curſed for having no fruit when he came to ſeek ſome from it, dried up immediately from the top to the roots; ſo a ſpiritual rottenneſs doth immediately and inſenſibly ſpread over their parts and gifts, and ſpiritual abilities. How can it be otherwiſe? for the Spirit of God which gives life to all, ceaſeth from his common workings in them: when the ſoul leaves the body, it haſtens to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefaction preſently; ſo doth a Chriſtian wither and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay, when the Spirit of God leaveth him. That curſe which <hi>David</hi> wiſhed to the mountains of <hi>Gilboa,</hi> on which <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Jonathan</hi> were ſlain, falls upon backſliders; <hi>Ye mountains of Gilboa, let no rain nor dew fail upon you:</hi> ſo God ſaith of ſuch as fall away from him, let not the dew of my Word fall upon thy heart any more; hear thou, but never underſtand my Word more. He that goes from <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> to <hi>Jericho,</hi> ſhall ſurely fall among Thieves, and loſe his raiment, and be wounded. Grace is like the leaves of a tree, when they fall off from the tree, winter cometh on immediately. See what backſliders are termed in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture; they are called <hi>degenerate Plants and ſtrange Vines,</hi> Jerem. 2.21. <hi>Reprobate ſilver ſhall men call them,</hi> Jerem. 6.30. they are like land-floods that run violently, and ſpend their ſtrength as quickly, and ſoon dry up, <hi>Job</hi> 6.15. they
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59782:20"/> are compared to Summer-fruits that ſoon putrifie, <hi>Amos</hi> 8.1, 2. our Saviour compareth them to ſhallow-rooted corn, that ſoon withereth for want of depth of earth, <hi>Math.</hi> 13.20. they are called <hi>empty vines,</hi> bringing forth fruit to themſelves, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 10.1.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful was the hand of God upon <hi>Spira</hi> and <hi>Latomus</hi> of <hi>Lovain,</hi> whoſe minds be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>led with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, unto their end cryed out, that they were dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and rejected of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that againſt their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience they had fallen from the truths of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel!</note>5. Becauſe of Gods dreadful exemplary revenge which ſometimes he executeth upon ſuch as fall away from him, filling their conſciences with horrour, and their ſouls with final deſpair of mercy: time was when they had ſome flaſhy comforts in duty, but this ſpring is now dried up from them, the Spirit of God is departed from them, and an evil ſpirit from the Lord is fallen upon them, as it did on <hi>Saul,</hi> tormenting them with horrour, and poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them with dreadful apprehenſions of inevitable and intolerable damnation. Who can conceive what <hi>Boaner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> what ſons of thunder their conſciences become with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their boſoms, continually crying out upon them, Oh wretched creature what haſt thou done! whom haſt thou forſaken? what! haſt thou caſt off thy God, thy Lord? haſt thou forſaken the fountain of living waters? haſt thou forſaken him who is the God of peace, the God of comfort, of happineſs, of all goodneſs? I muſt tell thee, God hath forſaken thee, and he will ſay to thee, Receive within thy ſelf the determinate ſentence of damnation which the Court of Heaven hath irrevocably paſſed upon thee. Moreover God ſometimes executeth ſome outward remarkable judgment upon revolters; <hi>Lot</hi>'s wife had been in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and not poiſoned with the ſuperſtitions of <hi>Egypt,</hi> lived in <hi>Sodom,</hi> and not polluted with the ſins of <hi>Sodom,</hi> ſhe was delivered from the errours of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r,</hi> delivered from the captivity of the five Kings, and at laſt delivered from periſhing with the Cities of the Plain; yet after all this ſhe forſook her own mercy, and periſheth in the ſin of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; therefore ſaith our Saviour, <hi>Remember Lot</hi>'s <hi>wife,</hi> Luke 17.32.</p>
               <p n="6">6. However the preſent dealings of God are with back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliders, yet in the end they ſhall certainly fall into ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59782:20"/> deſtruction, from the glorious preſence of that God, whoſe gracious preſence they deſpiſed in this life; God will then puniſh their departure from him with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, he will then ſay to them, ſeeing ye have depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from me, ye ſhall depart from me; you have departed from my ways, from my truths, from my worſhip, now <hi>depart from me ye workers of iniquity; Go ye curſed;</hi> none ſhall ſtay you: ſeeing you (as the Angels) fell from your firſt eſtate, you ſhall now receive the condemnation of the Angels, you ſhall fall into Hell with them; you fell from your ſeeming grace, you ſhall now fall from my real mercy into the hands of my juſtice. Apoſtacy is nothing elſe but a falling from the arms of God into the hands of the living God; and how fearful a thing it is to fall into his hands, let <hi>Judas,</hi> let the Divels from Hell ſpeak; for it is beyond the imagination and expreſſion of man.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. LEt the firſt Uſe of this Point be for caution to you; take heed to your ſelves leſt you thus fall away: ſpiritual caution is a ſpecial prevention of falling away, neceſſary (if ever) now to be preſſed upon you: Now here I ſhall ſhew you what you muſt eſpecially take heed of, that ye may ſtand, and not fall away.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Take heed of unbelief. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.12. the Apoſtle tells us, that the Jews were excluded from Gods reſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their unbelief; God ſware in his wrath that they ſhould not enter into his reſt; that was terrible; <hi>let us take heed therefore leſt there be in any of us an evil heart of unbelief in departing from the living God:</hi> An evil heart of unbelief it is an Hebraiſm, put for the evil unbelieving heart, where the Apoſtle deſcribeth unbelief by an elegant <hi>paranomaſia,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Unbelief is the cauſe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:59782:21"/> and root of total and final apoſtacy, and departing from God, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.10, 11, 12. where the Apoſtle ſheweth the cauſe of that great apoſtacy which was to be in the Church at the diſcovery of Antichriſt, and why Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian lies ſhould more prevail with men then the truths of the living God, namely their unbelief, they received not the truth in love, and they believed not the truth. What was the cauſe of the rich young mans departing from Chriſt, but his unbelief? he was not perſwaded he ſhould have life eternal, if he ſhould ſell all that he had, and give to the poor; wherefore he went away ſorrowful: So <hi>Alexander</hi>'s caſting off his faith, and a good conſcience (which is the Ark wherein God lays up this precious Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na) was the cauſe why he proved ſuch an enemy to <hi>Paul,</hi> and became a final and an irrecoverable Apoſtate. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief is the cauſe alſo why men in times of trial fall off from God, and decline the holy profeſſion of his truth; for God hath times of trial of his peoples faith and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion; as,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. When a mans worldly advantages and the ways of God are put to the queſtion, whether you will forſake Chriſt and embrace this preſent world, or embrace Chriſt and forſake the world, and that there is a neceſſity of one, unbelief will put a man upon the choice of the world, and the rejection of Chriſt; unbelief put <hi>Demas</hi> upon this choice, had he believed the promiſe of life eternal, he would not have embraced this preſent world: no unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving heart will follow Chriſt when worldly advantages fail; give them no more loaves, they will make no more profeſſion.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Times of perſecution are trying times; unbelief makes many a man to fall off, and to depart from God in times of Goſpel-troubles, when Religion is in diſgrace, and the Profeſſors thereof are troubled: When <hi>Paul</hi> was brought before <hi>Nero,</hi> at his firſt anſwer no man ſtood by him, but all men forſook him: Thoſe hearers in the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Sower, that are repreſented by the ſtony ground,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:59782:21"/> they heard the Word gladly, made a fair profeſſion for a time; but when perſecutions and afflictions aroſe, in time of temptation or trial they fell away, becauſe they had no root in themſelves, they were not by faith rooted in Chriſt; they heard the Word gladly, but did not mingle the Word with faith. Reproaches and perſecutions for the Name of Chriſt, are the bluſtering and ſtormy winds that drive the Ship of a temporary faith upon the rocks, and bring an irrecoverable ſhipwrack upon it: if you do not in ſuch times as theſe, heartily believe and cloſe with Gods promiſes, you will certainly fall: Gods way of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warding his Servants for the preſent is more by promiſe then by pay; if therefore you will not reſt in his word, you will fall from his ſervice: Unbelief in the heart, like the worm in the root of <hi>Jonah</hi>'s gourd, will make your Religion wither in a ſhort time. <hi>Fides eſt nervus Religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> faith is the ſinew of Religion; if the ſinew ſhrink, Religion will ſhrink. <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s ſtrength lay in his locks; the whole ſtrength of Religion lieth in the lock of faith; if luſt or the world cut off that, you will (as <hi>Sampſon</hi>) grow as weak in Religion as other men are.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II.</head>
                  <p n="2">2. Take heed of profeſſing Religion for carnal ends, either to enrich or advance your ſelves; take heed of fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Chriſt for loaves, of crying up Religion as <hi>Deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trius</hi> and his rabble did <hi>Diana,</hi> for ſilver ſhrines; take heed of the wicked ſuppoſition of corrupt men, that gain is godlineſs, that profeſs godlineſs for gain-ſake; becauſe if godlineſs brings no gain in according to expectation, ſuch a Profeſſor will fall from Religion to follow after gain. Doubtleſs <hi>Judas</hi> propoſed gain as the end of his Diſciple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; ſo when he ſaw Chriſt would not enrich him, then he would betray Chriſt, and the Phariſees ſhould: the Scripture noteth this of him, who when he was angry at <hi>Mary,</hi> becauſe of the ointment which ſhe beſtowed on
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:59782:22"/> Chriſt, pretending it was better that it had been given to the poor, not that he regarded the poor, but becauſe he had the bag. It is conceived by Interpreters, that the forward man that ſaid to Chriſt, <hi>Maſter I will follow thee whitherſoever thou goeſt,</hi> Math. 8.19, 20. when he hears Chriſts anſwer <hi>(The Foxes have holes, and the Birds of the air have neſts, but the Son of man hath not whereon to lay his head),</hi> that he forſook Chriſt; if Chriſt hath no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment for him, then he will have no regard of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. Such men think not that God is an heart-ſearching God, who if he ſeeth carnal ends and worldly luſts che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed in the heart, and covered over with a religious mantle, will in time uncaſe ſuch Hypocrites, pluck off their mask of godlineſs, and diſcover their baſe ends and luſts unto the world to their ſhame: Fooliſh worldlings! ye miſtake Chriſt in propoſing great things to your ſelves in ſerving him; becauſe he plainly tells you of loſſes, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, perſecution and poverty; he ſheweth you all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the world: it is the Divels way to preſent to us the glory of the world. He that takes up the profeſſion of Religion with love to it, will ſtand to it whatever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of it, he will leave worldly riches to cleave to poor truth; as <hi>Muſculus</hi> that forſook great preferments at <hi>Lut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zelſtein</hi> Abbey, to become a Preacher of the Goſpel in a poor Village, where he had not a bed to reſt upon, but was fain to lye on ſtraw, and to dig in the Town-ditch to get bread for himſelf and family; he was a man of a choice ſpirit, and of eminent parts and learning: It is otherwiſe with the unſound Chriſtian, he will keep on the ſhore, and not launch too far into the deep, but ſo that if a ſtorm ſhould ariſe, he might ſoon get to land a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III.</head>
                  <p n="3">3. Take heed of laying an ill foundation at firſt: Ill foundations are ruines of ſtately buildings; ill foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:59782:22"/> of profeſſion are the ruine of many eminent Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, ſo reputed. <hi>Math.</hi> 7. if we lay not the foundation in broken-heartedneſs, in faith, in ſincerity, in love to the Goſpel and the ways of Chriſt, called by our Saviour a <hi>building on the rock,</hi> but lay it in duties, in religious edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, in parts and gifts, called by Chriſt a ſandy foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, great will be the fall of ſuch Profeſſors in ſtormy times. A broken-hearted, ſincere, believing Chriſtian, is the ſtout and ſtanding Chriſtian. Pools will ſoon dry up, if there be not a ſpring to feed them; ſo Chriſtianity will wither away, if there be not a principle of grace within to feed it; there muſt be ſomething within to ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble us to a conſtant progreſs in a religious courſe. <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> ſaith, that the Heavenly Orbs keep their courſes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, becauſe they are moved by Intelligences: but I am ſure, a Chriſtian will move conſtantly in his Chriſtian Orb, if the Spirit of grace whirl him about; without this many forward Profeſſors are like the Almond-tree, that firſt bloſſometh, and is the firſt that is pinched with froſt: Many looſe Chriſtians never gave up themſelves fully to Chriſt, therefore they ſtay not long with him: Grace (ſaith a Judicious Divine) is one of thoſe rare things that laſt long, and ripen by leiſure:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Torſhel</hi>'s Hypocr.</note> He that takes up Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion for by-ends, that mans profeſſion will ſoon have an end.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Take heed of making an extemporary profeſſion of Religion, to profeſs Religion on a ſudden, in ſome heat or humour: Many men begin to build Towers, and to wage war with Principalities and Powers in heavenly pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces without premeditation what the charge and danger will be: It is Chriſts own advice, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.28. that when we go to build an houſe, we ſhould firſt ſit down and conſider what it may coſt us, and whether we be able to finiſh it. There are ſuch fooliſh builders in the Church, who on a ſudden raiſe up a religious ſtructure, without conſidering what it will coſt them; if Religion be like to coſt ſuch a man his credit, his profits, pleaſures, his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59782:23"/> and life, he then falls off. So likewiſe there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch religious Souldiers, who begin to wage a religious war, and never firſt conſider that they muſt conteſt with a hating, ſcoffing, contradicting world of enemies, againſt Divels, and Divels incarnate; therefore when God in his providential diſpoſals and commands puts them upon ſuch hard ſervice, they leave the field, and forſake Chriſt their Captain. A man that ſeriouſly thinks before-hand what Religion will c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt him, what oppoſitions he muſt meet withal, will hold out, he will go on undauntedly: I know (ſaith he before hand) I ſhall be ſcoff d at for Religion; I know I ſhall be hated of all men; I know that if I will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus I muſt ſuffer perſecution; I know I muſt bear the Croſs if I will be a Chriſtian, and part with my life too; Therefore ſhall ſuch a man as I flye?</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Take heed of conſulting with fleſh and blood in matters of godlineſs; ask their counſel, and they will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe thee to take heed of niceneſs, of ſtrictneſs, of ſingula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity (as they call Religion) leſt you undo your ſelf and yours, like <hi>Peter</hi>'s advice to our Saviour, <hi>Maſter pity thy ſelf;</hi> or it may be give the like advice; or perhaps give thee deſperate advice, ſuch as <hi>Job</hi>'s wife gave him, Curſe Religion, and dye; make no more ado. Our Saviour would by no means ſuffer the Diſciple when he called him, to go to his friends again, <hi>Math.</hi> 8.22. leſt they by their carnal advice might have drawn him away from following Chriſt. Carnal advice was the ruine of <hi>Spira.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. Take heed of a fruitleſs performance of holy duties, of giving way to ſpiritual deadneſs and formality in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious ſervices: a barren fig-tree will be cut down, a dead tree will be pluckt up by the roots.<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. Homil. in Math.</note> 
                     <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds the ſheep-skins which wolves have on them, to be heartleſs, formal performances: What are the ſheeps-clothing, ſaith he, but counterfeit ſhews of Religion, counterfeit alms, counterfeit prayer, counterfeit faſting? That man that ſerves God heartleſly, finds no ſweetneſs in his ſervice; where there is no reliſhing of the goodneſs
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:59782:23"/> of Gods ſervice, it is much if ſuch fall not away.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Take heed of ſtanding at a ſtay in Religion, and of non-proficiency in Religion: It is an Axiom in Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, That not to go forward, is to go backward: <hi>He that is not with me, is againſt me; he that gathereth not with me, ſcattereth,</hi> ſaith our Saviour: He that goes not forward in Religion, goes backward, ſaith <hi>Leo.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Leo Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note> The ſtate of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> is like a Ship ſailing with the wind againſt the ſtream; now if the wind be ſtronger then the ſtream, it is carried againſt the ſtream; but if the wind ſlacken, it ſtands not ſtill, but goes backward: So it is with a Profeſſor that is gone thus far, and hath ſet up his reſolution to go no farther, he ſoon declines and goes backwards.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. A Second Uſe ſhall be of Expoſtulation with thoſe that are ready to fall away from God: Our Saviour ſpeaks to you as he did to his Diſciples, when the multitude forſook him, <hi>Will ye alſo go away?</hi> will ye go away with the <hi>Judaſſes</hi> and <hi>Demaſſes,</hi> why ſhall you and I part hands? why will ye caſt me off from being your God? look from the ends of the world, and ſee whether there be any God like unto me; if there be, then go and ſerve that God: what will ye put your hand to the plough, and look back? if ſo, you judge your ſelves unworthy the Kingdom of Heaven. O remember the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation that we ſtand in to Jeſus Chriſt! Is not he the great Shepherd and Biſhop of our ſouls, and ſhall not the ſheep hear the voice of the Shepherd and follow him? Is not Jeſus Chriſt the husband of his Church, and ſhall not the wife dwell with the husband? Is not Jeſus Chriſt the hen to gather her chicken under her wings, and ſhall not the chicken come under her wings, and keep there? yet how many are there that run away from Chriſt, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:59782:24"/> ſo many bonds to tye them to him! Conſider, that the Angels in Heaven are glad with the converſion of a ſinner, and ſhall we make them ſad at our Apoſtacy, if they could be ſad; and make the hearts of Divels glad? O let it not be ſaid of you, as <hi>Paul</hi> of the <hi>Galathians, Ye did run well for a time,</hi> O what hath bewitched or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorted you that ye are turned aſide! Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Where I am there ſhall my ſervant be alſo:</hi> Are ye willing to be with Chriſt hereafter, and will you not follow him here? do you think to run away from him here, and be with him in Heaven? if you leave him, he can ſoon have other and better followers, but be ye ſure ye ſhall never find ſuch a Saviour, ſuch a Maſter again. Conſider how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing God is to part with you, though you have been guilty of ſome revoltings; <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11.7, 8. ſee how God ſaith in the like caſe, My people are bent to backſliding from me, <hi>&amp;c. How ſhall I deliver thee up Ephraim? how ſhall I deliver thee, Iſrael?</hi> thou art bent to backſliding, and deſerveſt I ſhould give thee up, yet I cannot tell how to do it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3. LEt me now call upon lapſed and backſliding Chriſtians to take notice of their ſad conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and bewail their loſs: Take that counſel given to the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> Rev. 2.4, 5. <hi>Remember from whence thou art fallen,</hi> and from whom thou art departed; thou art departed from God the fountain of life. If a ruſh go out of the water, it quickly withereth; and if a ſoul de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from God, it will ſoon decay: Let all thoſe that are in this eſtate, bewail their ſad condition: Time was, they were as trees planted by the rivers of water, ſpreading and flouriſhing, their fruits were fair and full; but now they are become as trees in the wilderneſs, in a forlorn eſtate; their ſweet Spring is turned into a ſad Autumn; their
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:59782:24"/> firſt days were their beſt days, and their laſt their worſt days: Time was, they were full of livelineſs in Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; but now they are cold and dead, their halcyon days are fled away, and the bonds of death have taken hold of them: Ah! let ſuch a one ſay, My heart was once the Temple of God, and the Throne of Chriſt, I had ſweet commerce with God, receiving lively oracles from his mouth daily; but now I ſit in the region of darkneſs: time was, his ſtatutes were my ſongs in this vale of <hi>Boehim;</hi> but now I taſte no ſweetneſs in them: while I kept cloſe with God, the tears which I abundantly poured forth were as pleaſant waters to me; but now the fountain is ſtopp'd, and theſe ſtreams are dried up and gone: my heart was wont to melt in duty; but now my comfort is gone, and that heart that was once an heart of fleſh, is now become an heart of ſtone: Oh what is become of the chain of graces that were linked together within me? where are thoſe operations of faith? where is that lively hope? where are thoſe overflowings of love that once I had? where are thoſe holy deſires, thoſe heavenly rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, thoſe enflamed affections, thoſe heavenly ejaculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, thoſe ſpiritual diſpoſitions, that once met in a bleſſed conjunction in my ſoul? I that was once under the guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dianſhip of Angels, am now conſtrained (like <hi>Daniel</hi>) to lie down in the den of horrour among devouring Lions: Time was, I had recourſe to God, and oh how ſweet was the repaſt I had in his preſence! but now my God is gone, my glory is departed! I entreat thee, O backſliding ſoul, to remember from whence thou art fallen, and lament thy doleful eſtate, and reckon that in this condition thou art more miſerable then thoſe that never taſted that God is gracious, becauſe once thou waſt in a happy condition; <hi>Miſerum eſt fuiſſe faelicem;</hi> it is a miſerable thing once to have been happy: The wicked think they are well enough without God, becauſe they never knew what it was to enjoy him; but this is the backſliders miſery, that he hath loſt him whom once he did enjoy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:59782:25"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIV.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 4. LEt me now perſwade backſliders to return to God; reſolve with the Church, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.7. <hi>I will go and return to my firſt husband; for then it was bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with me then now:</hi> make haſte to recover out of this ſad eſtate, the buſineſs requires ſpeed; what the Angel ſaid to <hi>Peter,</hi> I ſay to you, <hi>Ariſe quickly,</hi> Act. 12.7. while you are in this condition you are at a great and conſtant loſs; you loſe much peace, much inward ſtrength, many refreſhings from Gods Spirit, many love-tokens from Chriſt, many taſtes of ſpiritual delights; therefore make haſte and return, do as the Diſciples, when Chriſt called them, they left all and followed him; and as <hi>David,</hi> when for a time he had declined; <hi>I thought on my ways, and turned my feet to thy teſtimonies,</hi> Pſal. 119.59, 60. <hi>I made haſte, and delayed not to keep thy commandments:</hi> Oh do not delay your returning to God! if your hearts tempt you to delay, conſider that delay is but a modeſt denial; when men have a mind to put away repentance, they put it off: God requires a preſent returning to him, the long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er you delay, the deeper you run into Gods debt, and run the more under the power of ſin. I will propound a motive or two to encourage ſuch perſons to return.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Conſider Gods willingneſs to receive ſuch as return to him: <hi>David</hi>'s heart longed to go forth to meet his ſon <hi>Abſalom;</hi> the Father of the Prodigal made haſte to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and welcome his ſtraying ſon, that went from him into a far Country, and rejoyced that he that was loſt, was found again: God calls upon ſuch to return; <hi>Return ye back-ſliding children:</hi> Oh that every backſlider could ſay with the Church, <hi>Behold we come unto thee; for thou art the Lord our God,</hi> Jerem. 3.22.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Turn to him, and he will heal all your backſlidings, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.4. There is no Phyſitian in heaven or in earth
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:59782:25"/> can cure this falling-ſickneſs, but God only: he will not only heal you by the application of the blood of Chriſt to pardon you, but alſo by the application of his Spirit of grace to renew and eſtabliſh you in grace; and when the Lord healeth his peoples backſlidings, he will never upbraid them with what they have done; he looks upon backſliding <hi>Ephraim</hi> upon his repentance, as a pleaſant child, and though God ſpake againſt him, yet his heart is ſtill upon him; <hi>I remember him ſtill, I will ſurely have mercy upon him,</hi> Jerem. 31.20. But if after all this you will not return, the Lord may ſhut you up in a deſperate ſtate for ever: <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.21. <hi>I go away</hi> (ſaith Chriſt to the obſtinate Jews) <hi>and you ſhall ſeek me, but you ſhall dye in your ſins:</hi> Oh conſider, that hereafter you may find God as inexorable as now you are obſtinate, and then though you ſhould ſeek him, he may leave you to dye in your ſins, and then wo unto you if you dye in ſuch a condition; then <hi>the back-ſlider in heart ſhall be filled with his own ways,</hi> Prov. 14.14. Backſliders <hi>ſhall eat the fruit of their own way, and be filled with their own devices; the turning away of the ſimple ſhall ſlay them,</hi> Prov. 1.31, 32.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XV.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 3. I Come now to the third Propoſition; <hi>viz.</hi> That every godly man is to take heed leſt he fall from that meaſure of grace which he hath received. We muſt not ſpill a drop of oil out of our lamps, but muſt be daily increaſing it: God commandeth a growth in grace, is angry when he ſeeth the leaſt withering. In the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling this Point, I will firſt ſhew</p>
               <p>How a godly man may fall.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A man in the ſtate of grace cannot, and ſhall not fall away from that ſtate, his mountain is too ſtrong to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved; ſtorms may ſhake him, but they cannot beat him down, becauſe he is builded upon a rock; a man once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:59782:26"/> godly, and godly for ever; he is a mortal, yet im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortally gracious: I may ſay of grace, as <hi>Solomon</hi> of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, <hi>Prov.</hi> 9.1. <hi>She hath builded her houſe, and hewen out ſeven pillars,</hi> on which grace ſtands ſo firm, that all the powers of Hell cannot totally ruinate it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The pillar of Gods eternal election unto the ſtate of grace and glory is impregnably ſtrong: <hi>The foundation of the Lord ſtandeth ſure,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.19. That diſtinction is a meer dream, and not a Scripture revelation, of an electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to grace only, ſuch may fall away; and an election to grace and glory, ſuch cannot fall away: but if God hath elected any man to holineſs, he is elected to happineſs, election to a ſtate of grace is to a ſtate of glory.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The pillar of Gods unchangeable love to his choſen ones ſo firmly upholds the Saints, that they ſhall never fall away from that ſtate: The Lord telling his peo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le, that he would have mercy on them with everlaſting kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſaith, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 54.9, 10. <hi>For this is as the waters of Noah unto me,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>the mountains ſhall depart, and the hills be removed, but my kindneſs ſhall not depart from thee, neither ſhall the covenant of my peace be removed, ſaith the Lord.</hi> The Sea is not ſo full of water, nor the Sun of light, as this place is of love and comfort to the Saints: God ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hors that it ſhould be ſaid of him, that he is an uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant lover of his people.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The pillar of Gods and Chriſts unconquerable pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. his omnipotency is a ſtrong guard about the grace which his Spirit worketh in us; for ſo the Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifieth; Gods power is their ſtrong garriſon. Chriſt ſaith of his ſheep, <hi>I give unto them eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, and they ſhall never periſh, neither ſhall any pluck them out of my hand; My Father which gave them me is greater then all, and none is able to pluck them out of my Fathers hand,</hi> Joh. 10.28, 29. The power that muſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſs your hearts of grace, muſt be ſtronger then God and Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The pillar of an inſeparable union with their Head
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:59782:26"/> Chriſt: He and his members are more firmly knit toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then any natural head and members can poſſibly be: the head may be ſevered from the body; the arms or the legs may be cut off, or rent aſunder by wild beaſts; but all the ſtrength of all the Divels in Hell cannot rend a member from Chriſt; they ſhall as ſoon ſeparate his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine nature from the humane nature, as a living member from his body myſtical.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The pillar of Chriſts effectual and eternal redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of them firmly upholds grace in us, till he hath conſummated their redemption; it were no better then a temporary redemption of his people, ſhould they again return from grace to captivity to ſin and Satan.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The pillar of Chriſts unceſſant interceſſion in the behalf of his choſen people. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.11.15. he always makes interceſſion for his Church and people; and God the Father always heareth Jeſus Chriſt in their behalf.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The ſeed by which God regenerateth his children is immortal, <hi>by the word of God which liveth and abideth for ever,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23. and <hi>this ſeed remaineth in them,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.9. neither can they ſin, becauſe they are born of God; they may ſin themſelves out of Gods favour, but not out of grace; they may ſin themſelves into Gods anger, but not into his hatred: when <hi>Solomon</hi> gave himſelf to follow his hearts deſires, yet then his wiſdom remained with his, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2.9. God once repented that he had made man, but never repented that he beſtowed his grace upon any: <hi>The gifts and calling of God are without repentance, Rom.</hi> 11.29. if God never repents of giving, they ſhall never loſe that precious gift of his grace. Upon theſe pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars our ſtate of grace reſteth, there is no falling from it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:59782:27"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVI.</head>
               <p n="2">2. YEt notwithſtanding, though a godly man cannot fall from the ſtate of grace, yet may he fall from that meaſure of grace which he hath; the day-ſtar of grace may go back like the Sun in <hi>Ahaz</hi> dial 10 degrees, but ſhall never ſet; the Saints may go back from many degrees of love, but ſhall never fall from love it ſelf; the ſpring of living waters may run low, but ſhall never dry up: Chriſt told <hi>Peter, I have prayed for thee, that thy faith may not fail,</hi> yet we ſee it did ſhake; <hi>non rogavit ut ne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficeret, ſed ut ne prorſus deficeret;</hi> his prayer was not, that there ſhould be no failing at all, but that there ſhould not be an utter decay.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A godly man may fall from the vigorous exerciſe of his graces; this is an infallible conſequent of the former; for the actings of grace are proportionable to the meaſure; if ſtrong, then vigorous actions; if weak, then weak acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: a decay of vital operations follows the decay of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſpirits: the leſs the flame is, the leſſer is both the heat and light of the fire. He that is ambitious to put forth eminent acts of grace, muſt labour for an eminent mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of grace; he that deſireth to believe as <hi>Abraham</hi> did, muſt have the like meaſure of faith as he had: a weak child cannot put forth manly acts. Of this kind of fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a godly man muſt take heed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. Becauſe of the excellency of grace: as it is ſaid of truth, <hi>Quiſquilia veritatis ſunt precioſae,</hi> the ſweep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of truth are precious; ſo it may be ſaid of grace: the very filings of gold are precious; one grain of grace is more worth then all the world; one act of faith is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then ſilver, then fine gold, more precious then rubies; all things a man can deſire are not to be compared to a dram of grace: a man is loth to loſe the head of a pin that is made of gold, nor the ſmalleſt piece of a diamond;
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:59782:27"/> ſhall a godly man be careleſs of the leaſt degrees of grace, more worth then a Mine of gold or a rock of diamonds? See how careful the wiſe Virgins were, they would not ſpare one drop of their oil, though to ſave the ſoul of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother: an Angel would ſooner part with his glorious joy, then part with a drop of grace: he that truly know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the worth of grace, and only he, will ſooner part with a drop of his hearts blood, then with a drop of grace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2. Becauſe of the ſad effects which undoubtedly follow falling from the meaſure of grace.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Though you ſhall not loſe your union, yet you may loſe your ſweet communion with God and Chriſt; ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and doleful deſertion is ſometimes the reward of your ſpiritual decays: God withdraws his favour for your withdrawing from his grace, that when you ſigh out your ſad complaints, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> God anſwereth, becauſe thou haſt forſaken thy firſt love, thy firſt zeal: Oh rather juſtifie me, and condemn thy ſelf, and ſay, O my God I have forſaken my firſt love, therefore haſt thou forſaken me; the fountain of life hath forſaken me, becauſe I have forſaken him!</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond ſad effect is the loſs of your comfort; the loſs of your inward joy and peace follows the loſs of your graces; ſpiritual joy and comforts do ebbe and flow according to the ebbing and flowing of grace; the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows of Hell are ſometimes the chaſtiſement of the loſs of the grace of Heaven: want of grace doth not occaſion ſorrow ſo much as the loſs of grace. What the Papiſts feign of Purgatory and the Souls there, <hi>viz.</hi> that there be two rivers, one of fire, and the other of water; when the ſouls are vehemently ſcorcht with the heat of the fire, they leap into the river of water, when they freeze with cold, they leap into the fire; this may be an emblem of a godly man: decays of grace tranſlate him out of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of comfort into Hell flames; the recovery of grace tranſlates him from ſorrow into joy again: He that will
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:59782:28"/> maintain his peace and comfort, let him maintain his graces.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Great temptations unto ſome great ſin, do follow men upon falling from their meaſure of grace, and Gods denying aſſiſting grace at that time, that ſometimes they fall into ſome ſin which waſteth their conſciences: As Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians to cure a man of the Lethargy, do let him fall into a burning fever; ſo God to cure our decays, ſuffers us ſometimes to fall into ſome dreadful ſin, that being hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled we may revive our graces. As <hi>David</hi>'s enemies ſaid of themſelves, <hi>Let us purſue him, let us overtake him, for God hath forſaken him;</hi> So the Divels cry out of a decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſtian, let us purſue him, let us overtake him with ſome ſtrong temptations; for God hath forſaken him.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Sometimes great afflictions overtake us, when we decline in grace: God deals with his own children as <hi>Gideon</hi> did with the men of <hi>Succoth,</hi> Judg. 8.16. <hi>He took the elders of the City, and thorns of the wilderneſs and bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars, and with them he caught the men of Succoth:</hi> So God with the briars and thorns of afflictions teacheth his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and makes them know the bitterneſs of falling from their graces; by ſuch means a recovery is wrought in them, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.6.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Your luſts grow through the decay of grace: Luſts and grace are in us as two buckets in a well; if the bucket of grace goes down, ſin riſeth up. Your Gardeners ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve of trees planted neer together in a fat ſoil, if the one withereth, the other flouriſheth the more: it is true of grace and ſin; If grace decay, ſin will flouriſh the more; if you delight not in the graces of Gods Spirit, he will make you to groan under the burden of your luſts; if you do not believe as formerly, he will make you to cry out, Oh my curſed unbelief! if you do not walk humbly with God, he will make you cry out, Oh my curſed pride, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. A decay in all duties of godlineſs followeth a decay in your graces: Grace makes the wheels of your chariots run gallantly; the more grace in your hearts, the more
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:59782:28"/> activity in prayer, the more ſpiritual ſtrength in all ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſervices: loſe grace, and you loſe your ſtrength; you cannot pray as formerly, becauſe you believe not as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly; you are not fervent in prayer, becauſe you are not zealous as heretofore: the leſs oil is in the lamp, the more dimly it burneth: you cannot expect a great heat from the fire, if you take out the fuel that maintaineth it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 3. Conſider the folly of this courſe; the grace that ye loſe you muſt repair again, if you deſire commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God again, or deſire to recover your joy and comfort, or your ſpiritual ſtrength again: as a man climb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ladder, falling from many rounds, can never get to the top, till he hath recovered the very ſtep from which he fell; ſo it is in our fall from grace, we muſt never look to enjoy what we formerly had, till we recover that meaſure of grace from which we fell.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. THe firſt Uſe is of Exhortation: You that think you are in the ſtate of grace, and have abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the Spirit poured out upon you, have a watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful eye that ye ſpill not a drop of the grace of God; it is Gods own image, will ye not be careful to keep that from the leaſt defacing? it is the divine nature, will you part with that? it is the blood royal of Heaven, loſe not a drop of it: Do you deſire to maintain communion with God, to walk in the light of his countenance, to be filled with the joy of Chriſt? do you deſire to run like a Giant the courſe of Chriſtianity? then take heed of falling from that meaſure of grace you have received.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What muſt we take heed of, that we fall not?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. Take heed of the neglect of holy duties: Watermen ſay, they loſe more by miſſing one ſtroke, then they can gain by many: So may a Chriſtian loſe more by neglect of one duty, of one Ordinance, then he can gain
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:59782:29"/> by many: that man will not grow rich in grace, that grows poor in duty; the praying, the hearing, the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating Chriſtian, is the thriving Chriſtian: as in nature, the ſeed brings forth the flowers, and the flowers bring forth the ſeed, if one fail, both will fail; ſo in grace, the ſeed of ſaving grace brings forth the flower of ſpiritual duties, and the flower of ſpiritual duties brings forth the ſeed and fruit of grace.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Take heed of remiſsneſs in duty; remiſsneſs in grace will follow upon it; in praying we muſt pray, in hearing hear; ſerve God with all your might, then God will ſtrengthen us with all might in the inner man; that man that doth not exerciſe his graces in duties, will loſe his graces; he that prays not in faith, will loſe faith in praying: it is an heavy curſe, if a man in ſeeing ſee not, and in hearing hear not; it is no leſs, when a man in praying prayeth not.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Take heed of over-much love of the world; the love of the world is a cauſe of total apoſtacy from God, as we ſee in <hi>Judas</hi> and <hi>Demas:</hi> he that is too careful in ſeeking the things of the world, will be too careleſs in ſeeking the things of Chriſt. The <hi>Arabians</hi> have a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, <hi>Claude feneſtras ut luceat domus,</hi> Shut the windows that the houſe may be lightſom: So ſay I, ſhut your eyes from beholding the glory of the world, that your ſouls may gliſter with grace: why doth our Saviour ſo often give forth Caveats againſt covetouſneſs, but becauſe he knoweth earthly employments are heavenly impediments?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Take heed of pride, becauſe of your graces; for pride goes before a fall: Angels and <hi>Adam</hi> were too proud of their glorious gifts, and they fell fearfully; God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure pride in any thing, though it be grace it ſelf: God to prevent pride in <hi>Paul</hi> ſent a meſſenger of Satan to buffet him. When the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperour ſaw the people grow ſo proud as to wear jewels in their ſhoes, he took them away: Beware therefore of pride, and always re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that God reſiſteth the proud, and giveth grace to the humble.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:59782:29"/>5. Take heed of ill principles and ill opinions; corrupt opinions and principles deſtroy holy practices; ſome dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous opinions entertained have brought a great decay of grace upon many Profeſſors: it is the Divels policy to buſie the heads of many about opinions, that the heart may ſit looſe in holy practices.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Take heed of ſelf-confidence: <hi>Peter</hi> fails in his faith, becauſe he was too confident of his love to Chriſt: That ſoul doth moſt ſtrengthen his grace, who liveth in an holy fear of decaying in grace; he that hath a jealous fear over his own heart, will be moſt watchful over it: where there is a fear of decay, there is the greateſt circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection; God hath the greateſt communion with ſuch, who are afraid to depart a ſtep from him.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Beware of ſpiritual niggardlineſs in laying out your graces; the more grace you lay out, the more increaſe; <hi>To him that hath ſhall be given, and he ſhall have more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance:</hi> having there is put for uſing; for the unfaithful ſervant had a talent, but did not uſe it; this is the talent in the napkin, to have grace, and not to uſe it: he that is ſlothful in improving grace, decayeth in grace; improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of every thing is the advancement and increaſe of it; money is increaſed by improvement, ground is made fruitful by improvement; ſo is grace alſo increaſed by an holy improvement of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. That you may not fall from the meaſure of grace you have received, labour to grow in grace; and to this purpoſe,</p>
               <p n="1">1. See that you grow up in Chriſt in all things by the operation of the Spirit of Chriſt upon your ſouls, which Spirit is as the ſoul of the new life within you, ſo enlarg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and corroborating every ſpiritual member, that it may be a meet inſtrument of righteouſneſs to bring forth fruit to God; be not like a Giant in a painted cloth, that never attained to thoſe dimenſions by any growth from any vital principle; but be ye in your ſpiritual growth in proportion like the humane nature of Chriſt in his child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:59782:30"/> encreaſing in wiſdom and ſtature, and in favour with God and man, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.52. ſee that grace have the ſame efficacy upon your ſouls, which the ſoul hath upon the body; while the body is in a growing condition, the ſoul enlargeth the body in all the parts and dimenſions of it, that the members may not only fill more cloaths, but take in more nouriſhment, and ſo be more ſtrengthened and fitted for ſervice.</p>
               <p n="2">2. See that you grow not only without, but alſo from within; to live under the powerful diſpenſation of the Word, to converſe with lively and growing Chriſtians, men may catch ſomething here and there that may make them ſeem to grow, and by obſerving their ſhining con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations and godly examples, they may endeavour to be like them; they may be bigger in notions, in words and phraſes, in the outward garb and motion of a Chriſtian, but in the mean time wither and decay within; ſuch mens diſcourſes of God and Religion are but like the pratings of Parrots, being taught by others, they ſpeak like men, but know not what they ſay: If ye will increaſe in all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes of God, as you have your nouriſhment from without, ſo your growth muſt be from within; if you firſt grow within, you will then grow without: ſee that ye be firſt engraffed into Chriſt by the Word of God, then from Chriſt the heart will draw out ſo much nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment, as that Chriſt ſhall be formed in you, and from thence you will grow and become fruitful in your conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, not only in bringing forth the leaves of profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but alſo the fruits of obedience to God. A ſeeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly growing Chriſtian grows not at all in the inner man, but in the outward parts only; it is only (as one noteth) like the growth of the hair and nails, which Nature puts forth as excrements of the skin and outward parts, which grow even when a man is dead, as long as there is any moiſture to feed upon: It is not enough to grow external<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, unleſs we have alſo internal growth; if we have no more but the growth of knowledge, of zeal and affection,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:59782:30"/> and ſome outward formalities, it is but as a wen in the body, or an exuberance in the blood that ſeeks vent by the pores; ſuch knowledge the Scripture accounteth no knowledge, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.2. ſuch zeal no zeal, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.2. and ſuch grace to be no grace, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.21. ſuch a one, like the Church of <hi>Sardis,</hi> hath a name that he liveth, but is indeed dead, even dead while he liveth. See that your growth proceed not from the excreſcency of nature and corruption, but from the divine nature in you.</p>
               <p n="3">3. See that you grow every day more fruitful, that you go from faith to faith, from ſtrength to ſtrength; that ye grow in grace, not for a fit and ſtart, or for a humour, but for continuance upon ſetled reſolution and ſerious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation; ſee that you hold on in your way (as it is ſaid of the righteous man) and grow ſtronger and ſtronger, <hi>Job</hi> 17.9. that ye be always going forward toward per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, that your good works be moe and better at laſt then at firſt, that ye grow more fruitful in old age, even fat and flouriſhing; it is not enough that ye bear fruit, but ye muſt bring forth the beſt fruit at laſt; the Lord ſtill beſtoweth more husbandry, and is at more coſt upon them that do ſtill abound in the fruits of righteouſneſs, that being purged they may bring forth more fruit, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.2. as trees of the Lords planting, the older you grow, ſee that ye be the more fully laden with the fruits of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, <hi>being filled with all the fruits of righteouſneſs which are by Jeſus Chriſt unto the praiſe and glory of God,</hi> Phil. 1.11. although your outward man decay, ſee that your inward man be renewed day by day: Oh how many Profeſſors of Religion are there that grow very faſt at firſt, but ſoon wither like the ſeed caſt into the ſtony ground, as that did for want of depth of earth, for lack of root! <hi>Jonah</hi>'s gourd was up in a night, and became a great ſhadow to him, but there was a worm at the root that ſmote the gourd, that it alſo withered; ſo ſome ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret luſt lying in the heart, blaſteth a forward ſpring of profeſſion in many Chriſtians.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:59782:31"/>4. See that your growth in grace be a proportionable growth; the formal Chriſtians growth is like the growth of a child that hath the Rickets, that is big in the head, but thriveth not in any other parts of the body; ſo many ſeeming Chriſtians are big in knowledge, but little in conſcience, full of ſeeming zeal, but little in judgment and diſcretion; yea one part is the occaſion of the decay of another; as in the body of man the increaſe and ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the ſpleen, cauſeth the body to languiſh; ſo where there is only a ſeeming growth in grace, true love to God and his ways utterly decayeth: ſee therefore that your growth be proportionable in every part; there is an effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual working from the Head in the meaſure of every part: every Chriſtian is a member and a part of Chriſt; and all his members are the fulneſs of Chriſt; and every part muſt aſpire to the nature and figure of the Head in his proportion, that it may be a model and reſemblance of the whole body, which is the fulneſs of him that filleth all in all: ſee that every part and piece of each part grow in Chriſt, that when you grow in knowledge, you grow in grace alſo, and by growing in grace you will grow more in ſpiritual knowledge; there is no true growth in the one without the other: be ſtill therefore <hi>adding to your faith virtue, to virtue knowledge, and to knowledge temperance, and to temperance patience, and to patience godlineſs, and to god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs brotherly kindneſs, and to brotherly kindneſs charity;</hi> and be ye careful <hi>not only that theſe things be in you, but that you abound in them,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.5, 6, 7, 8. It is true, ſome Chriſtians have been more eminent then others in ſome one particular grace; <hi>Abraham</hi> was eminent for his faith, <hi>Moſes</hi> for his meekneſs, <hi>Job</hi> for his patience, <hi>David</hi> for his zeal, <hi>John</hi> for his fervent love to Chriſt: as it falls out in the parts of the body, ſome have a ſtronger arm, ſome a better leg, another a taller ſtature, another a more love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly countenance; they may have ſome one or other part that may more affect the ſpectator, yet all comely and holding a good proportion: ſo it ſhould be among Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:59782:31"/> in the endowments of the ſoul; ſome may excell more in one grace then in another, but if your growth in grace be kindly, no one grace will hinder the growth of another, or render any unſerviceable or diſproportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the reſt. There is no body that is altogether per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, ſo that it is wholly free from obſtruction or diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in ſome parts of it; neither is there any ſoul here ſo exact, but that there may be an obſtruction of ſome gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in their growth, ſo that ſome graces may not hold pace with the reſt: ſome violent diſtemper in the body may be an impediment to a childs growth for a while; ſo ſome dregs of corruption may obſtruct our ſpiritual growth, which being purged away, a Chriſtian grows more fruitful afterward.</p>
               <p n="5">5. See that your growth in grace be more then a ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing growth, that it be a real growth; ſee that ye be not like ſtakes or poſts pitch'd in the ground, ſtanding as if they grew, but grow not; be not you like thoſe women the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, <hi>ever learning and never coming to the knowledge of the truth,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.7. but as thriving plants in Gods Orchard labour to increaſe more and more; and like the Vine that ſhoots out as far as he can, while either the wall or the pole will help him along.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
